<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A banquet of ieasts. Or Change of cheare Being a collection of moderne jests. Witty ieeres. Pleasant taunts. Merry tales.</title>
            <title>Banquet of jests. Part 1.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855710</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 773:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A banquet of ieasts. Or Change of cheare Being a collection of moderne jests. Witty ieeres. Pleasant taunts. Merry tales.</title>
                  <title>Banquet of jests. Part 1.</title>
                  <author>Armstrong, Archie, d. 1672, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Neuer before imprinted.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[24], 192 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Royston, and are to be sold at his shoppe in Ivie-Lane next the Exchequer Office,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Anonimos; sometimes attributed to Archie Armstrong.</note>
                  <note>Contains 195 jests.</note>
                  <note>The headlines contain "Part 1".</note>
                  <note>The words "moderne jests. .. Merry tales." are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English wit and humor.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BANQVET OF IEASTS. OR Change of Cheare. <hi>BEING</hi> A COLLECTION OF Moderne Jeſts. Witty Jeeres. Pleaſant Taunts. Merry Tales. Neuer before Imprinted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Ivie</hi>-Lane next the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer-Office.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER, whom I deſire to be as <hi>Courteous</hi> as <hi>Conceited.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you (of all ſorts) that ſhall vouchſafe the peruſall of theſe few ſheetes ſtitcht vp in a ſmall fardell, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare you to expect no more in this collection of Ieſts, then the Title page promiſeth, wherein is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing earneſt, ſauing a
<pb facs="tcp:21212:3"/> pledge of my good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towards you. If you looke that I ſhould feaſt you ſenſes, or banquet your particular Pallates, theſe Papers will much deceiue you: For in the ſtead of dainties you ſhall finde <hi>Dicteria:</hi> for Iunkets, <hi>Ioci:</hi> and for curious Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, <hi>Sales.</hi> Onely they are paſſages of myrth, fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine time, and imploy leaſured houres, when they cannot bee more ſeriouſly and profitably imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So milde and gentle they are in their condition,
<pb facs="tcp:21212:3"/> that as they barke at none, ſo they bite not any: and therefore you may ſport with them freely, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Now if ſome out of their curioſitie ſhall deſpiſe them for their common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; I muſt then retire my ſelfe to the refuge of that old Adage, <hi>Bona quo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munia eo meliora:</hi> If they prooue good, they cannot be too common. Againe, if any ſhall obiect and ſay, that I know that, and this I haue heard related; Thoſe I thus anſwer. If many haue heard ſome of them, but
<pb facs="tcp:21212:4"/> few or none (I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume) all. Beſides I doe not challenge them for mine owne, but gathered from the mouthes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and what is ſtale to mee, may bee to thee new. Accept them then as cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly as they are offered to thy peruſall willingly, to make them familiar vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch to whom they are meerly forraigne, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect the memories of thoſe to whom they have beene knowne, but ſince forgotten. I muſt ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly confeſſe vnto you,
<pb facs="tcp:21212:4"/> that had not the Licence curbed my libertie, the leaves of this booke had beene more in tale, and the Ieaſts (for I know not how more properly to ſtyle them) greater in number: But as they are (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe now they cannot be) if they bee well accepted, I acknowledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too few, but if not well receiued, by many, too many.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anonimos.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Contents of the paſſages herein mentioned.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. OF a Country-man and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.</item>
               <item>2. A caſheird Captaine.</item>
               <item>3. Of a Iuſtice of Peace, and a Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtealer.</item>
               <item>4. The Principall of an Houſe.</item>
               <item>5. M Gentleman arreſted.</item>
               <item>6. A Batchelours anſwer touching Mariage.</item>
               <item>7. A Counſellor, and his client.</item>
               <item>8. Of an Oatemeale man.</item>
               <item>9. A Gentleman and a Barber.</item>
               <item>10. A wager of eating.</item>
               <item>11. Two Welſhmen in a robbery.</item>
               <item>12. Geneva print.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>13. A Papiſt and a Puritane.</item>
               <item>14. A young Heire.</item>
               <item>15. Of a Gentleman comming to Court.</item>
               <item>16. Of a Freeſe Ierkin.</item>
               <item>17. A Poore man arraigned.</item>
               <item>18. Two old Captaines.</item>
               <item>19. A great Eater.</item>
               <item>20. A Gentlewoman and a Iuſtice.</item>
               <item>21. A Nobleman in his Gallery.</item>
               <item>22. One trauelling to Rome.</item>
               <item>23. A Scholler on horſe-backe.</item>
               <item>24. A Gentleman, and a Citizen.</item>
               <item>25. A Clarke of a Church.</item>
               <item>26. A Cheeſe-monger.</item>
               <item>27. Of a Doctors man.</item>
               <item>28. A Boy that cryed fire.</item>
               <item>29. A Countrey fellowes courteſie.</item>
               <item>30. One with a great Noſe.</item>
               <item>31. One that ate of a Beare.</item>
               <item>32. An Engliſh man at a French Ordinarie.</item>
               <item>33. Of a Seruingman.</item>
               <item>34. Of a Iuſtice and his man.</item>
               <item>35. A Cheater and a Tapſter.</item>
               <item>36. A man on the Gallowes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>37. Two by the eares.</item>
               <item>38. A drunkard and his wife.</item>
               <item>39. A Theeſe and a Gentleman.</item>
               <item>40. A rich mans Hoſpitall.</item>
               <item>41. To chuſe a wife.</item>
               <item>42. Of a Horſe, and a Pecke of Oyſters.</item>
               <item>43. A famous Theefe.</item>
               <item>44. A young Maſter of Arts.</item>
               <item>45. A ſimple Country-man.</item>
               <item>46. A Courtier.</item>
               <item>47. Two Schollers.</item>
               <item>48. Gentlemen at a Taverne.</item>
               <item>49. A Chronologer.</item>
               <item>50. The Mariage of the Arts.</item>
               <item>51. Of a Scholler maried.</item>
               <item>52. An Epitaph.</item>
               <item>53. Of an extraordinary noſe.</item>
               <item>54. Two Inkeepers.</item>
               <item>55. Two old Widowes.</item>
               <item>56. A Horſe-ſtealer.</item>
               <item>57. A Baker.</item>
               <item>58. A Coachman.</item>
               <item>59. A Taylor.</item>
               <item>60. A Cheater.</item>
               <item>61. A handſome wench, and a Iuſtice.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>62. A clearly lye.</item>
               <item>63. Gentlemen at an Ordinary.</item>
               <item>64. Of a deafe Hoſteſſe.</item>
               <item>65. Of a Prentice.</item>
               <item>66. A Spaniard and a Dutchman.</item>
               <item>67. A great Lords entertainment.</item>
               <item>68. An Empericke.</item>
               <item>69. Of a Horſe.</item>
               <item>70. A young Citizen and his Wife.</item>
               <item>71. Of Rape ſeed.</item>
               <item>72. Of a Thatcher.</item>
               <item>73. Of another Thatcher.</item>
               <item>74 Of an Oxe hide.</item>
               <item>75 Three Surgeons.</item>
               <item>76. Of Bucanon.</item>
               <item>77. An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer dying.</item>
               <item>78. A pariſh Clarke.</item>
               <item>79. Two ſiſters.</item>
               <item>80. Wiſhers, and woulders.</item>
               <item>81 Barbarous Latine.</item>
               <item>82 A Gentleman to a Lady.</item>
               <item>83. Two hyring one horſe.</item>
               <item>84. A Gentleman and a Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer.</item>
               <item>85. A man buying a Cow.</item>
               <item>86. A Doctor and a Lady.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>87. An Epitaph.</item>
               <item>88. Pope Alexander VI.</item>
               <item>89. Pictures hang'd.</item>
               <item>90. Comming of the Spaniards.</item>
               <item>91. A father and his daughter.</item>
               <item>92. A letter writ out of the Countrey.</item>
               <item>93. A lye retorted.</item>
               <item>94. A Scotchman and his Miſtris.</item>
               <item>95. Of a Gentleman that was the firſt of his houſe.</item>
               <item>96. An Empericke and his man.</item>
               <item>97. Two Country Fellowes.</item>
               <item>98. A Churchman in his Inne.</item>
               <item>99. An Engliſh Gentleman in France.</item>
               <item>100. A Gentlemen and a Conſtable.</item>
               <item>101. A rich man and a poore.</item>
               <item>102. A ſleepy drawer.</item>
               <item>103. A famous Painter.</item>
               <item>104. Of giuing away Deere.</item>
               <item>105. The King a hunting.</item>
               <item>106. Of choughing in ones graue.</item>
               <item>107. A Gentleman in diſgrace.</item>
               <item>108. A ſimple Conſtable.</item>
               <item>109. The twelue ſignes of vſury.</item>
               <item>110. One preaching againſt vſury.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>111. Of a tall Gentleman, and a little Taylor.</item>
               <item>112. Two Gentlemen falling out.</item>
               <item>113. A Drunkard.</item>
               <item>114. A Maſter of a ſhip.</item>
               <item>115. A Gormandizer.</item>
               <item>116. A Welch Reader.</item>
               <item>117. A Biſhop and a Gentleman.</item>
               <item>118. Truſting for a reckoning.</item>
               <item>119. A Strange beaſts to be ſeene.</item>
               <item>120. A Emperour of Rome.</item>
               <item>121. A Scotch Witch.</item>
               <item>122. A braggard.</item>
               <item>123. The reuerſion of an houſe.</item>
               <item>124. A Mayor in the North.</item>
               <item>125. A man lying ſicke.</item>
               <item>126. Of one Fowle a Gentleman.</item>
               <item>127. A Gentleman in an Ordinary.</item>
               <item>128. A Welchman and a Cutpurſe.</item>
               <item>129. A Gentleman and a Parſon.</item>
               <item>130. Of Graue Maurice, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe Spinola.</item>
               <item>131. Of Biſhop Gardiner.</item>
               <item>132. An vnhappy Vintners Boy.</item>
               <item>133. Of a ſigne.</item>
               <item>133. Playing with words.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>134. Of a Landlord and his Tenant.</item>
               <item>135. Of an old Beggar.</item>
               <item>136. A rich man and a Scholler.</item>
               <item>137. A Lawyer and a Diuine.</item>
               <item>138. Of Swimming.</item>
               <item>139. Of a ſhe-ſeruant that came to take her oath.</item>
               <item>140. Another Gentleman and a Parſon.</item>
               <item>141. A Lawyer at the Barre.</item>
               <item>141. A Mayor in the North.</item>
               <item>142. The Tenant to an Archbiſhop.</item>
               <item>143. Of a ſigne.</item>
               <item>144. Of a Tranſlator.</item>
               <item>145. A Marriner in a ſtorme.</item>
               <item>146. A deſperate Saylor.</item>
               <item>147. A ſhort Cloake.</item>
               <item>148. Of Wine.</item>
               <item>149. A Welchman arraigned.</item>
               <item>150. Of Card-playing.</item>
               <item>151. An Epitaph made vpon an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Cobler.</item>
               <item>152. Of a Gentleman viſiting of his friend.</item>
               <item>153. Of a Captaine that was to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>154. Of two knaves accuſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
               <item>155. Of a Vintners boy.</item>
               <item>156. Of Auguſtus Caeſar.</item>
               <item>157. Of Diogenes.</item>
               <item>158. Of a Country fellow and a Peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree.</item>
               <item>159. Stratford vpon Auon.</item>
               <item>160. An old Gooſe.</item>
               <item>161. An honourable Theefe.</item>
               <item>162. Of S. P. Q. R.</item>
               <item>163. An Oppreſſour.</item>
               <item>164. A wrie Noſe.</item>
               <item>165. Of vſury.</item>
               <item>166. A Scholler and a Townſman.</item>
               <item>167. Of an ignorant fellow.</item>
               <item>168. An old horſe.</item>
               <item>169. Fire and Toe.</item>
               <item>170. Borrowing of a Cloake.</item>
               <item>171. One begd for a foole.</item>
               <item>172. A Traueller drowned.</item>
               <item>173. A Knight of Italy.</item>
               <item>174. A Gentleman boaſting of hic Wit.</item>
               <item>175. A Iuſtice and a Baud.</item>
               <item>176. Of a Citizen, and a Gardeners Boy.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>177 Anold Vicar.</item>
               <item>178. Two debawſht follewes.</item>
               <item>179. A lame Horſe.</item>
               <item>180. A Woman, and her Husband.</item>
               <item>181. A Townſman and a Scholler.</item>
               <item>182. Of fiue Vintners.</item>
               <item>183. Two ſtriuing for the Wall.</item>
               <item>184. The anſwer of a Doctor.</item>
               <item>185. A Horſecouſer.</item>
               <item>186. A Countrey fellow hunting with the King.</item>
               <item>187. Women Writers.</item>
               <item>188. A Country fellow at a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Table.</item>
               <item>189. Of curtaling names.</item>
               <item>190. A retort betwixt two Gentlemen.</item>
               <item>190. A Knight and his man.</item>
               <item>191. A Doctor of Phyſicke and a Seruing man.</item>
               <item>192. One that parted a Fray.</item>
               <item>193. A bargaine in Smithfield.</item>
               <item>194. An Vſurer dying.</item>
               <item>195. A Doctor and Scholler.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:10"/>
            <head>To the Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Now expoſe thee little Booke,</l>
               <l>To all that daigne on thee to looke,</l>
               <l>And doe not take mee for a Cooke,</l>
               <l>becauſe profeſſing</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You haue an Ordinary here,</l>
               <l>(For which you ſhall not pay too deare)</l>
               <l>And yet be ſeru'd with change of chear,</l>
               <l>and of my dreſſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet tell them they are inuited gueſts,</l>
               <l>And ſeldome meet they with ſuch feaſts,</l>
               <l>Where nothing is diſht in but ieſts,</l>
               <l>and ſauc'd with laughter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They ſhall not meet I dare compare,</l>
               <l>(Where Geeſe &amp; Pigs are nothing rare)</l>
               <l>The like in Bartholmews next Fayer,</l>
               <l>nor the day after.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:11"/>
               <l>I wiſh it may not be your lots,</l>
               <l>(Poore Pupes) to be rent by ſots,</l>
               <l>Or ſuch as will ſtop Muſter pots,</l>
               <l>for that beleeue me,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would like a Chandlers greaſie fiſt,</l>
               <l>Who raps his wares in what be liſt,</l>
               <l>As well in things applaus'd as hiſt,</l>
               <l>no little grieue me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>T' were better thou ſhouldſt Critticks meet,</l>
               <l>Whoſe very lookes will ſower what's ſweet.</l>
               <l>Who though they carpe at euery ſheet,</l>
               <l>nay page, or pagine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſooth I ſhall not much admire,</l>
               <l>Though they with thee Tobacco fire,</l>
               <l>For ſo perhaps ſome may deſire,</l>
               <l>as I imagine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Much nobler 'tis to ſuffer ſo,</l>
               <l>By ſuch as ſomething ſeeme to know,</l>
               <l>But wherefore in ſuch rage to grow,</l>
               <l>Ile not compell them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21212:11"/>
               <l>So farewell Booke, I make thee free,</l>
               <l>To ieere at them that ieſt at thee,</l>
               <l>Though thou be hurt it harmes not me:</l>
               <l>prethee ſo tell them.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="jokes">
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21212:12"/>
            <head>Change of Cheare, <hi>OR</hi> A Banquet of Ieſts.</head>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>1. Of a Country-man and a Conſtable.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Simple Country-man hauing terme buſines in London, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat late a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the night, was ſtaid by a Conſtable, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what harſhly entreated, the poore man obſeruing how imperiouſly he commanded him, demanded of him what hee was: to whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, I am the Conſtable, and this is my Watch. And I pray you ſir,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21212:13"/> for whom watch you? (ſaith the man) marry anſwered the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I watch for the King; for the King replyes he againe ſimply? then I beſeech you S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. that I may paſſe quietly and peaceably by you to my Lodging, for I can bring you a certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate from ſome of my neighbours who are now in towne, that I am no ſuch man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>2. A caſheird Captaine.</head>
               <p>A Captaine in the Low-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries being Caſheird and his company conferred vpon another, hee grew more priuate and Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, and not long after being met by the others Leiftenant, was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaluted, and after other comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, demanded why hee was of late ſo ſtrange, to abſent himſelfe ſo long from his Captaine; who much deſired to ſee him: who anſwered I pray you commend me to your Captaine, and tell him he had my pany too late.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21212:13"/>
               <head>3. Of a Iuſtice of Peace, and a Horſe-ſtealer.</head>
               <p>A Horſe-ſtealer was brought to bee examined before a Iuſtice, who finding the fellony to be moſt apparent, Well friend ſaith hee; if thou beeſt not hangd for this fact, Ile bee hangd for thee. I humbly thank your Worſhip; replyed the theefe, and when the time comes, I deſire you, that you will not be out of the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>4 The Principall of an Houſe.</head>
               <p>A Pleaſant fellow came vnto the Principall of a houſe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that hee had receiued ſome iniury by ſome of the Societie, complained vnto him in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Sir, ſaid hee, I have beene abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a company of Raſcals, belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to this Houſe, and knowing you to bee Principall, I thought
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21212:14"/> good to acquaint you with the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and ſo proceeded, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>5. A Gentleman arreſted.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman being arreſted and brought before a Country Maior, who was by Profeſſion a Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, being ſomewhat roughly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Sergeants, and eſpying an Oxe hide in the place where they ſtayd him till the Maior was ready to come forth, My freinds, quoth hee, what neede you trouble your ſelues ſo much about me, when me thinkes you had more neede, and it would better become you, to bruſh your Maſters Gowne that lyes on the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>6. A Batchelours anſwer touching Mariage.</head>
               <p>A Lady obſeruing a Gentleman that was a Batchelour, much giuen to Melancholy, ſaid vnto him,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21212:14"/> truely Sir, I am of opinion, that you will neuer be truly merry till you bee maried: to whom hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: In troth Madam I am of opinion that I ſhall neuer laugh till my heart ake, till then.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>7. A Counſellor, and his client.</head>
               <p>ONe making a long and tedious ſpeech to a graue Counſeliour, in the concluſion thereof made an Apology to excuſe himſelfe for being ſo troubleſome, who gaue him this anſwer, Ile aſſure you ſir, you haue not beene troubleſome to me at all, for all the time that you were ſpeaking, my minde was of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>8. Of an Oatemeale-man.</head>
               <p>AN Oatemeale-man a rich fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low fell at ſome difference with a Comedian about the towne, and began to vpbraid him with his profeſſion, and according to the ſmall talent of wit hee had, came
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21212:15"/> hotly vpon him with the common obiection, if, ſaith he, all men were of my mind, you ſhould keepe your doores ſhut, and find your galleries empty, and then you would bee more poore, and leſſe proud. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, replied the other, ſo if eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man would, as I could find in my heart to doe, that is, to forſweare the eating of Puddings, and Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, who would be more poore, and leſſe proud then the Oatemeale man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>9. A Gentleman and a Barber.</head>
               <p>A Barber comming finnically a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Gentleman, was (as the moſt of them are) terribly full of talke, at length hee found the leiſure to aske how hee would bee trimmed. Marry my friend replyed the gentleman, if thou canſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, doe it in ſilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21212:15"/>
               <head>10. A wager of eating.</head>
               <p>TWo Captaines, the one an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the other a Dutch man, hauing both good ſtomacks, laid a wager which of them at one ſet dinner ſhould eate moſt. Earneſt was giuen, and they drew lots which ſhould beſpeake their Prouant; it fell to the Dutch man, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently went downe into the Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and beſpoke of the Hoſteſſe of the ordinary a fat Capon and a dozen of Larkes, and ſo came vp againe to his company: Preſently the Engliſh Captaine went downe to enquire what hee had ſpoke for. The Hoſteſſe told him, A Capon &amp; a dozen of Larkes. How? ſaith hee. I ſay, hoſteſſe, ſend into the Market and buy for vs a dozen of Capons, and a Larke. Of which the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hearing, grew preſently to compoſition, and recanted the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21212:16"/>
               <head>11. Two Wolſhmen in a robbery.</head>
               <p>TWo Welſhmen were in a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, and both taken: the one being knowne to bee an old theefe, had his iudgement to bee hanged, and was ſo. The other, becauſe it was his firſt fault, found the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and had his ſentence to bee whipt at a Carts-taile, and ſo let go. Who after, comming into his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and being demanded what was become of his friend and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, hee told them for a truth that hee was marryed: but ſome not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing it, and further preſſing him to know when and to whom: hee anſwered he could reſolue them no further then this, that hee was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly marryed; by the ſame token, before a great many Spectators, hee was forced to dance at his wedding</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21212:16"/>
               <head>12. Geneva print.</head>
               <p>A Collection being made for the diſtreſſed Miniſters of Geneva a Gentleman, which (it ſeemes) was not much affected towards them, being preſt by the Collector ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hard for his charitie, he abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely told him hee would giue him nothing. But the other, not ſo ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, would needs know his reaſon: The Gentleman after ſome pauſe, anſwered him, If you will needes know my reaſon, it is becauſe I finde nothing more preiudiciall to my eye-ſight then the reading of their Geneva print.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>13. A Papiſt and a Puritane.</head>
               <p>A Papiſt &amp; a Puritane being next neighbours, and travelling by the high-way where ſtood a wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Croſſe: the papiſt put off his hat, and ſo paſſed by: At which his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21212:17"/> neighbour onely ſmiled to himſelfe and ſaid nothing. But walking fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and paſſing by a tree that ſtood in the way, and not ſeeing him move to that, Neighbour (ſaith he) I pray you in courteſie will you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue mee a queſtion. With all my heart replyed the other, ſo that if occaſion be offered, youle doe mee the like: both are agreed, now then neighbour ſaith the Puritane. I would know why you did not the like reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the tree: that you did vnto the Croſſe, being both one wood: the reaſon of this (ſaith the other) you ſhall ſoone know, but one thing firſt I muſt know of you: I called vpon you in the morning, and I obſerued you in taking leaue of your wife, why did you kiſſe her lips and not her taile ſeeing they are both made of one fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21212:17"/>
               <head>14. A young Heire.</head>
               <p>A Young heire not yet come to age, but deſirous to bee ſuited with other gallants, and to bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht with money and commodities to the purpoſe: the creditor deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his bond, hee granted it condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, that his Father ſhould not know of it, therefore wiſht it to bee done very priuately. Vpon this promiſe all things were concluded: and the time came when he ſhould ſeale it. But when hee beganne to read in the beginning of the bond, <hi>Nouerint vniuerſi.</hi> Be it knowne vnto all men, he caſt away the bond &amp; abſolutely refuſed to ſeale it ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: If it be knowne vnto all men, how can it poſſibly bee but it muſt come to my Fathers care.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21212:18"/>
               <head>15. Of a Gentleman comming to Court.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman comming out of the Country, and hauing one <hi>Mr</hi>. Wiſeman to his Kinſman who liued in the Court, and belonged to the King, came bluntly to the Guard-Chamber, and ſpeaking to him that kept the doore: I pray you ſir tell me (faith he) is not there one Wiſeman among you? who anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, No indeed ſir, you had beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the Queenes ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>16. Of a Freeſe Ierkin.</head>
               <p>AN honeſt good fellow hauing worne a thredbare Ierkin for the ſpace of two yeares &amp; an halfe: as ſoone as hee had compaſt another ſuite, for the good ſeruice it had done him, made of it this Epitaph.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Here lie in peace thou patient ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</l>
                  <l>Of two cold winters, and one Scortching Summer.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21212:18"/>
               <head>17. A Poore man arraigned.</head>
               <p>A Poore ſimple man arraigned at the Seſſions for his life, and being conuicted, the Iudges, much commiſerating him in regard of his ſimplicity, purpoſed to doe him what fauour they could, and offered him his booke: which he hearing, caſt himſelfe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his knees beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to doe him any fauour elſe ſauing that, for hee proteſted vnto them, that he could read no more then the Pope of Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>18. Two old Captaines.</head>
               <p>TWo ancient Captaines looking vpon the rich hangings of Eighty Eight, obſeruing in the border thereof, the faces of all the prime Commanders, and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of note that had beene in the ſeruice, Well, ſaith the one to the other, if euery one had his right,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21212:19"/> my face might haue had the honor, to haue bin placed before ſome that I ſee: for I am ſure I was ingaged in the hottedſt incounter. To whom the other replyed, content thy ſelfe Captaine, tis well knowne thou art an old ſouldier, and reſerued for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other hanging.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>19. A great Eater.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman riding downe into the Low country, was askt by his freind, what was the beſt newes at London, who anſwered them he had by reaſon of ſuddaine, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected comming downe not liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after any: onely wot you what (ſaith he) It is reported that ſuch a man, naming the great Gormandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer, hath loſt his ſtomacke to whom the other replyed: If a poore man haue found it he is directly vndone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21212:19"/>
               <head>20. A Gentlewoman and a Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>A Gentlewoman ſuſpected to be a Romiſh-Catholike; being brought before a buſie Iuſtice in the country, he would not accept of her oath, vnleſſe ſhe would publikely call the Pope knaue: to whom ſhee anſwered, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, if it pleaſe your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, it were great folly and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in me, to call any man knaue whom I neuer either ſaw, or knew, but I proteſt ſir, (ſaith ſhe) If I had ſeene him ſo often, or knowne him ſo well as I doe your good worſhip, I think I might, and with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience too, call him knaue, and knaue againe, and with this anſwere I pray you reſt ſatisfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>21. A Nobleman in his Gallery.</head>
               <p>A Priuate Gentleman being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to walke with a noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in his gallery being full of curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pictures, hee commended them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21212:20"/> exceedingly, as ſome of thoſe peices to bee the beſt that hee had ſeene: Say you ſo ſaith the nobleman, then out of all theſe, chuſe that which beſt pleaſeth you, and it is your own: the Gentleman eſpying a faire table in which the ten commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were curiouſly drawne in golden Letters: Pleaſe you my Lord, ſaith hee, of all that I haue viewed, this like I beſt; and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge by your promiſe. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord replyes. That onely I had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to except, chuſe elſe where you will, and it is at your free diſpoſe, but theſe I will neuer depart from. Why my Lord, ſaith the Gentleman, haue you vowed theſe ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements ſhall neuer goe from you. Indeed ſaith he I haue, and haue vowed it by mine honour; Wel replyed the Gentleman, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may ſpeake your pleaſure, but I will aſſure you and take my word, with all the care you haue, you ſhall neuer keepe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21212:20"/>
               <head>22. One trauelling to Rome.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman of England trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with his man to Rome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee all faſhions, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch rarities as were there to bee ſeene, was by the mediation of ſome friends there reſident, admitted into the Popes preſence: to whom his holineſſe offered his foote to kiſſe; which the Gentleman did with great ſubmiſſion, and reuerence: this his man ſeeing, and not before ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanted with the like ceremony, preſently makes what ſpeed he can to get out of the preſence: which ſome of the wayters eſpying, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting his haſt, ſtayd him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the cauſe of his ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ſpeed: but the more they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune him, the more he preſt to be gone: but being further vrged, he made this ſhort anſwer, truely ſaith he, this is the cauſe of my feare, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21212:21"/> if they compell my maſter, being a Gentleman to kiſſe the Popes foote; I feare what part they will make me kiſſe being but his ſeruing man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>23. A Scholler on horſe-backe.</head>
               <p>A Scholler an vnskilful rider being to paſſe throgh a riuer, offred to water his horſe before hee rid him in ſo deepe as to the foote-locke, his friend that was with him, fearing he would founder him, cald vpon him to ride in depeer, the other not well vnderſtanding his meaning, ſayd to his friend, firſt ſtay till hee hath drunke off all this, and then I will ride him in farther where hee may haue his belly full.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>24. A Gentleman, and a Citizen.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman &amp; a Citizen wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king together, iuſt before them went two Aldermen, ſaith the Gentleman to the other, there goes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21212:21"/> a Cuckold, at which the Citizen his ſuppoſed friend takes exceptions, and tells the others what was ſpoke, they make a complaint, and bearing him before the Maior, the parties appeare, witneſſe is called; the words iuſtified, the Gentleman hee pleades a miſtake, for ſaith he, I ſaid not by theſe two wòrthy Citizens there goes a Cuckold: but the words that I ſpake were, there goes a couple, I, was it ſo ſaith the Maior, if it were no otherwiſe, the matter is anſwered, and I here diſcharge you the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>25. A Clarke of a Church.</head>
               <p>THe Clarke of the Church, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued ſome diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Pariſh, grew ſullen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it, and when Sunday came, and that hee was to giue out a Pſalme: he ſate ſtill in his ſeat, &amp; would not ſo much as open his lips, but being often called vpon, and ſeeing there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21212:22"/> was no remedie, lookt ſomewhat doggedly vpon the matter: ſing you may if you pleaſe the <hi>Pſalm</hi> of <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque Vult,</hi> whoſoeuer will, and for his owne part, as ſoone as hee had giuen it out; went out of the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>26. A Cheeſe-monger.</head>
               <p>A Puritane comming to his neighbour, a Cheeſe-monger; to buy a Goſſips or groaning Cheeſe becauſe his wife was ready to lye downe, the maſter of the ſhop offerd him a taſte of that which he ſeemes beſt to like: who as he put it to his mouth, ſo he put his hat to his eyes, and began a long grace, which the Cheeſe-monger ſeeing, nay ſaith he, ſince you meane in ſtead of a taſt to make a meale out of my cheeſe, I aſſure you, you ſhall buy none here; for I cannot afford it after that waight and meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21212:22"/>
               <head>27. Of a Doctors man.</head>
               <p>AN old Doctor lying on his deathbed, willing to leaue ſomething to a poore ſimple ſeruant who had ſerued him long, to doe him ſome good after his deceaſe, wild him to profeſſe Phyſicke and hee would leaue vnto him certaine preſcriptions, both to benefit his knowledge and eſtate, amongſt others this was the maine, that ſtill when hee came to viſit any patient, he ſhould looke curiouſly about the roomes, what bones he ſaw ſcattered either about the Table or the beds ſide: if he found any of fiſh, then he ſhould tell him hee tooke a ſurfeit of ſuch a kinde of fiſh, as hee might gueſſe it to bee by the bones; and ſo likewiſe of Beefe, Veale, Mutton, Capon, and Rabbit, &amp;c. and to iudge by the fragments, and reuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which were more certaine, then to preſume vpon the diſeaſe by the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21212:23"/> ſicke mans water, in which he knew he was altogether vnpractiſed, and vnskilfull: In proceſſe it ſo fell out, that being ſent for to one that was ſick of an Impoſtume, and the roome being ſo cleane ſwept, that he could find no apparent ſigne in the floore, by which hee might coniecture of any certain diſeaſe, prying at length very curiouſly, beneath his bed hee ſpide and found a Saddle lie: vpon which, he came vnto his ſicke Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and ſeriouſly told him that hee had now ſearcht into the nature of his diſeaſe, for by feeling of his pulſe he might well perceiue hee had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a great ſurfet by eating of a horſe; at which the Patient fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch an extreame laughter that his Impoſtume broke, by which he was ſuddenly cured, and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low grew thereby more famous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21212:23"/>
               <head>28. A Boy that cryed fire.</head>
               <p>AN vnhappy boy lying in the ſtreets in a cold winter night, cryde fire, fire: the people lookt out of their Windowes, &amp; cryde where, where? marry quoth the Boy I would I knew my ſelfe, for I would gladly warme mee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>29. A Countrey fellowes courteſie.</head>
               <p>A Countrey fellow meeting with his friend told him he had beene at <hi>London,</hi> and ſeen my <hi>Lord Maior;</hi> I but ſaid his friend, did he take any notice of thee? no faith, ſaid he, no great notice, onely I put off my hat to him, and he did his duty to me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>30. One with a great Noſe.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman with an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary great Noſe, walking along <hi>Cheapſide</hi> an vnhappy Prentiſe Boy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21212:24"/> meeting him makes a ſudden ſtand, at which the Gentleman muſing, made a ſtand likewiſe, and asked him why hee did not keepe his way? to whom the Lad anſwered, Sir I would gladly paſſe by you, but I cannot for your Noſe; the Gentleman loath to bee too much obſerued, or to be the occaſion of any tumult in the ſtreet, with one of his fingers put his Noſe on the one ſide, and ſaid; now youth you may freely paſſe, the way lies plaine before you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>31. One that eate of a Beare.</head>
               <p>A Woman hauing eaten of the right ſide of a Beare, which ſome ſay makes good Veniſon, tooke a conceit, that ſhe had an exceeding great rumbling and rowling in her belly, and for remedy ſends to aske adviſe of the Doctour, who perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to knock a Maſtiffe Dog in the head, and eat ſo much of him,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21212:24"/> and ſo no doubt but the fleſh of him would worry the Beare in her belly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>32. An Engliſh man at a French Ordinarie.</head>
               <p>AN Engliſh man being in <hi>France,</hi> and at a French Ordinary, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other diſhes there were Woodcocks at the Table; the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomewhat before the time tooke one of the Woodcocks heads, and pickt it; which one of the Monſters obſeruing, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his wit to play vpon him; I haue (ſaith he) euer noted theſe Engliſh men, that whereſoeuer Woodcocks are ſerued in, their fingers will be euer firſt in the diſh, the reſt laught at the ieſt, and hee for the preſent made no reply: but when the Table began to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw and euery man was ſilent, the Engliſhman fell into a great laughter, and being demanded the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21212:25"/> reaſon of it: troth (ſaid he) at a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous good ieſt was made this night at Supper, which I proteſt hath ſo taken me, that I ſhall neuer hereafter ſee a Woodcock, but I ſhall either thinke of that Monſier, or ſome of his Countreymen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>33. Of a Seruingman.</head>
               <p>A Seruingman bringing a brace of Greyhounds from his Maſter to a Knight a friend of his, and a neere neghbour; the Knight asked him whether they were good Dogs or no? good Dogs (ſaith the fellow) I will aſſure you for this, pointing to the one of them, he is the beſt Dog that euer ran with foure Legs vpon the earth, and ſee you this other, hee is three times better then he.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21212:25"/>
               <head>34. Of a Iuſtice and his man.</head>
               <p>AN old Iuſtice of Peace and his Seruingman riding with other company vpon the way, the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomthing windy, a Crow ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon a weake and tender bough, which at euery ſmall guſt moued this way and that, and cryed as they rode by Ka, Ka, Ka: harke, ſaith the Iuſtice to his man, what the Crow ſaith to thee, ſhee would (if ſhee could) ſay Knave, Knaue: nay, not to me ſaith the fellow ſure ſhee meanes to ſome man of worſhip in this company, you may well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by her many low becks and congees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>35. A Cheater and a Tapſter.</head>
               <p>A Fellow that was exceeding drie, and had no money, came to a Taphouſe, and cals for a Can of Beere, and drinks it off; which done,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21212:26"/> he asked the Tapſter if hee had any bread, yes ſir, ſaith hee, you may have a whole dozen if you pleaſe, no (ſaith hee) halfe a dozen will ſerve, and bring it in; the Tapſter did ſo, and ſet them before him: now (ſaith he) becauſe I will giue thee a good account, bring me an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Canne of Beare, which was no ſooner done but hee dranke it off, and withall gaue him two pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Loaues, then call'd for the third, then for the fourth, till he had made it vp a full halfe dozen, and ſtill for euery Canne giues him a Loaſe; then asked him what was to pay. Sixe pence ſaith the Tapſter. For what ſaith the fellow? For Beare ſaith the Tapſter. Why, hadſt thou not bread for thy Beare, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the other? Why then for bread, ſaith the Tapſter. Hadſt thou not thy bread againe ſaid the fellow? how can that bee? So whilſt the Tapſter was ſtudying to reconcile this intricate recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21212:26"/> hee ſtept out of doores, and paid nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>36. A man on the Gallowes.</head>
               <p>ONe paſſing by, and ſeeing a poore fellow in a very cold morning vpon the Gallowes in his ſhire, and after a ſhort confeſſion rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be turned off the Ladder: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las poore man (ſaith he) I muſt pitty him, he will ſtand ſo long yonder in the cold, that I am affraid hee will goe neere to catch his death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>37. Two by the eares.</head>
               <p>A Man and a woman being toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the eares in the ſtreet, and a great throng about them; a Citizens wife paſſing that way by chance, demands of a Gentleman that came from the tumult, what the occaſion of that vproare might be? to whom he anſwered, you are a whore. How ſaid ſhe? thou art an
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21212:27"/> arrant Knaue to call me whore, I am as honeſt as the skinne betwixt thy brows: he preſently very courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put off his Hat, and ſaid, Truely faire Gentlewoman, this was the occaſion of their quarrell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>38. A drunkard and his wife.</head>
               <p>A Woman had a husband that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to come home often diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſometimes to lye along in the floore, and ſtill when ſhe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to raiſe him from the ground, he would not be remoued, but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, the tenement is mine owne, I pay rent for it, and I may lye where I liſt: Some few nights after, comming home in the like taking, he ſate downe in a Chaire before the fire, and fell aſleep: the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would haue waked him, but could not, and therefore went vp to bed; in which ſhee was ſcarce warme, but the maid cryed out aloud, Miſtris, Miſtris, my Maſter is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21212:27"/> falne out of the Chaire, and lyes in midſt of the fire: which ſhe hearing, lay ſtill, and anſwered, Let him alone, for as long as he payes rent for the houſe, he may lye where he will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>39. A Theefe and a Gentleman.</head>
               <p>A Theefe in the night hauing pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to rob a Gentlemans chamber which was three Stories high, had conueyed a ladder vp to his window, and being at the top of it, and ready to make his entrance, it happened the Gentleman at the ſame time was awake, and heard him, and iuſt as he was about to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Caſement, hee met him at the window, and ſaid, My friend, it is your beſt courſe to ſtay till an houre or two hence, for I am not yet aſleepe; which the Theefe hearing, what with haſt, and feare, tumbled downe from the top of the Ladder, and without the helpe of a halter had almoſt broke his necke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21212:28"/>
               <head>40. A rich mans Hoſpitall.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman comming by where a rich man was laying the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of an hoſpitall, whiſpered to his friend, and ſaid, I much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this man aboue many others that I know, for hee doth well to prouide for beggars now, knowing he is ſo neere his death, that by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion hath made ſo many in his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>41. To chuſe a wife.</head>
               <p>ONe being diſſwaded from marrying a woman, becauſe ſhe was no wiſer, made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, I deſire that the wiſe whom I am to marry ſhould haue no more wit then to bee able to diſtinguiſh her husbands bed from another mans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21212:28"/>
               <head>42. Of a Horſe, and a Pecke of Oyſters.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman hauing rid hard in a went morning, and comming into his Inne dropping drie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his money fell ſhort, loath to be at the charge of faggots, giuing his horſe to the Oſtler, he comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hall where was a great fire, but ſet ſo round, that he could not get ſo much as ſhoulder roome, for the weather being wet and cold no man would giue him place: he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpyed Oyſters at the Inne gate, called in great haſt to the Oſtler to give his horſe inſtantly a Pecke of Oyſters, for his purpoſe is to ride away before dinner: the Oſtler was amazed, the reſt wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but hee would not reſt till hee ſaw them meaſured, and caſt before his horſe into the Manger: ſtrange it was to them all to heare of a Horſe that would eate Oyſters, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21212:29"/> to behold the nouelty all of them preſently left the fire, and ran in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly into the ſtable, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim he warmes, and dries him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe throughly from top to Toe at his pleaſure, they gaping like fooles till he had what hee deſired, came backe againe, and told him his would not touch an Oyſter: no, ſaith he, will not the ſullen lade fall too, is not his ſtomacke yet come to him? well Oſtler take away his Oyſters, and giue him ſo many Oates, and bring that he ſcornes to eate hither to mee, and ſee what I can doe with them: which was done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; by that time the Horſe had made an end of his Oates, hee had done his Oyſters, the weather grew faire, and he well dryed, rode on his iourney.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21212:29"/>
               <head>43. A famous Theefe.</head>
               <p>A Famous Theefe frequenting one of our Cities, where the Gates were continually ſhut a nights, and not willing to lye in the Suburbs for feare of ſearch or ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, acquainted himſelf with one of the Porters of one of the Gates, and fed him with money, that ſtill when he had beene abroad about any exploit, that he ſhould be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to let him in at what houre ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and this he vſed a long time, till at length being taken, arraigned and conuicted for many robberies, and great euidences came againſt him: the next day he was brought to the Gallowes, where the Sheriffs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him ſtill to confeſſe more, and more; at length he deſired that they would ſend for this Porter, which was done accordingly: The poore man came quaking, and trembling, and the people were in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21212:30"/> great expectation of ſome ſtrange thing to be reuealed, all thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nouelty. By this time the Theefe vpon the ladder ſpies him, and cals him to him; the poor Porter in a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful fear asks why he ſent for him, and what he had to ſay to him? To whom the Theefe replyed; Troth honeſt Porter I onely ſent for thee to tell thee, that if I come not in by this and twelue a Clocke at night, doe not tarry vp for me, but goe to bed a Gods name, and ſaying no more, leapt off the Ladder, and with this ieſt in his mouth was hanged in earneſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>44. A young Maſter of Arts.</head>
               <p>A Young Maſter of Art the very next day after the Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hauing his courſe to common place in the Chappell, where were diuers that the day before had took their degree, tooke his Text out of the eigth Chapter of <hi>Iob;</hi> the words
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21212:30"/> were theſe, we are but of yeſterday, and know nothing. This text, ſaith he, doth fitly diuide it ſelfe into two branches, our ſtanding, and our vnderſtanding, our ſtanding in theſe words, wee are but of yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, our vnderſtanding, we know nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>45. A ſimple Country-man.</head>
               <p>A Simple fellow at an <hi>Eaſter</hi> time, comming to receiue the Communion, the Preacher hauing demanded of him diuerſe eaſie que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and finding him ignorant in all, at length askt him how many Commandements there were: hee anſwered hee could not tell. The Parſon wondring at his ſottiſh ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, askt him how many hee thought there were. Marry I thinke ſaith he, there may be ſome foure or fiue. Yes ſaith the Parſon there are more. Why then replyde he there may be ſeven or eight; but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21212:31"/> if you know better, then you had beſt tell me. Why then quoth hee, I will. There are iuſt ten. At which he laughed, and ſaid, Nay I thought ſo and looked for no leſſe, for ſure I was, that you being the Parſon, would bring them to ten, becauſe you would keepe the tythe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>46. A Courtier.</head>
               <p>ONe of our Scarlet Courtiers comming on a time prancing on a great horſe, and alighting at the Court gate, calls to one that ſtood by, and ſaith to him, I prethee honeſt fellow, whileſt I walke into the Court, doe ſo much as hold my horſe. The man ſeem'd afraid of the beaſt, and asked him withall, if hee was not unruly, and that one man might hold him, he anſwered yes, very eaſily. Nay then ſaith hee, if it be but one mans worke, I would wiſh you to doe it your ſelfe, for I haue more buſineſſe in hand, then walking of horſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21212:31"/>
               <head>47. Two Schollers.</head>
               <p>TWo Schollers of one Colledge in the Vniverſitie, the one called <hi>Paine,</hi> the other <hi>Culpepper,</hi> were both in fault, but <hi>Paine</hi> in the leſſe, the other in the greater: but when the fault came to bee cenſured, the fault was not leſſe then expelling the Colledge: but <hi>Culpepper</hi> the greater delinquent yet finding more friends, had his ſentence tooke off, and liberty to remaine ſtill in the houſe, but the other ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for example: A Maſter of Art of another houſe comming to viſit a friend of his that was of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge where this was done, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt other diſcourſe, askt what became of the buſineſſe betweene the two Schollers, hee told him in briefe, how <hi>Paine</hi> that was in the leaſt fault was puniſht, and <hi>Culpepper</hi> in the greater pardoned, who inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly replyed, Nay then I thinke <hi>Ovid</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21212:32"/> did Prophecie of this when hee ſaid,</p>
               <q>Paena perire poteſt, culpa perennis erit.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>48. Gentlemen at a Taverne.</head>
               <p>TWo or three Gentlemen meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a Taverne about ſome buſineſſe, and walking up into a roome two paire of ſtayres high, called for a pint of Wine, which being drunke off, and they often knocking and calling, but none ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwering, or comming up, one of the Gentlemen threw down the pint pot, when inſtantly a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er comes up with a quart, and ſo left them; they following their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and drinking to the good ſucceſſe of the bargaine they were then concluding of: the quart pot was likewiſe ſoone emptied, they knocke againe, and call, none an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, downe goes the quart pot, and in a trice comes vp a pottle,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21212:32"/> which after ſome reſpite being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpatcht, and they ready to call for a reckoning, and ſo to bee gone, as vnwilling to enter into further charges; they call aloud, but none would anſwer, then beat they the pottle pot againſt the table but none yet anſwered, at length they thundred with ſuch violence, that vp comes one of the drawers, whom a Gentleman being angry at ſuch ſlacke attendance, meets him at the toppe of the ſtaires, and caſts him headlong downe to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. At which all the reſt of his fellowes, with the Maſter of the houſe, beganne to muſter vp their ſelues, and comming vp into the Gentlemens roome, he demanding the reaſon of that violence done to his ſervant, one of the Gentlemen anſwered thus, Mine Hoſt, we have no way willingly tranſgreſt the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of your houſe, for we obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that calling for one pint of wine, and caſting downe the pot
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21212:33"/> you brought vp two; then caſting downe the quart pot, you preſented vs with a pottle: now ſitting here alone, and no man regarding vs to bring vs vp a reckoning, wee flung one Drawer downe the ſtaires, to no other purpoſe, but in hope to haue two at the leaſt to attend vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>49. A Chronologer.</head>
               <p>ONe of our late Chronologers that ſucceeded old M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn Stow,</hi> and others, in his briefe Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle ſpeaking of <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> ſaith, he was drowned in a Rundlet of Malmeſey, and being taxt by a Gentleman that he had mainly falſifyed the Hiſtory, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that <hi>Hollingſhed, Speed,</hi> and others haue delivered to the world that hee was drowned in a whole Butt, to which hee anſwered, that hee had no way erred from the truth, for if theſe that writ great and large Hiſtories, call it a Butt, he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21212:33"/> might (and no way improperly) in his ſmall Epitome of Chronicle, cal it a Rundlet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>5 The Mariage of the Arts.</head>
               <p>THe Play called The Mariage of the Arts being preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>Iames</hi> at <hi>Woodſtocke,</hi> he in regard that it was ſomewhat tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and himſelfe weary with ſo long ſitting, offered twice or thrice to goe away, which being obſerued by an ingenious Scholler of the other Vniuerſity, hee writ theſe verſes:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When Chriſt-Church ſhowd their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the King,</l>
                  <l>Leſt that their match ſhould want an offering,</l>
                  <l>The King himſelfe did offer: what I pray?</l>
                  <l>He offered twice or thrice to goe away.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21212:34"/>
               <head>51. Of a Scholler maried.</head>
               <p>A Scholler having married a yong wife, and being ſtill at his booke, preferring his ſerious ſtudy before dalliance with her, as ſhe was one day wantoning whileſt he was reading: Sir ſaith ſhee, I could wiſh my ſelfe that I had been made a booke, for then you would bee ſtill peering vpon mee, and I ſhould never night nor day bee out of your fingers: ſo would I ſweet heart, anſwered he, ſo I might chuſe what booke, to whom ſhe againe anſwered, and what booke would you wiſh mee to bee, marry ſweet wife ſaith he, an <hi>Almanacke,</hi> for ſo I might haue euery yeer a new one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>52. An Epitaph.</head>
               <p>THe Lord chiefe Iuſtice <hi>Femming</hi> that ſucceeded Iudge <hi>Poppans</hi> in his place, being both a learned
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21212:34"/> and mercifull Gentleman, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, a pleaſant fellow writ of him this Epitaph:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Iuſtice is dead, that was of Iuſtice chiefe,</l>
                  <l>Who neuer yet hang'd true man for a theefe:</l>
                  <l>Nor ever was condemned for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</l>
                  <l>Being borne in England, yet he dide a Flemming.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>53. Of an extraordinary noſe.</head>
               <p>A Pleaſant fellow meeting a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſtreet with an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie red noſe, lookes very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in his face, as if he had eſpied ſomething there which hee won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, the man askt what it was at which he ſo gazed, to which hee anſwered, friend, I haue reuiewed you thus earneſtly, and for ought I can perceiue, me thinkes your eyes are not matches, no ſaith he, I pray
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21212:35"/> ſhow a reaſon why they are not, marry ſaith he, becauſe moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they had beene matches, your noſe by this time would haue ſet them on fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>54. Two Innekeepers.</head>
               <p>AN Inkeeper of <hi>Saffron Walden</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing euery Term co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to one Inne in <hi>London,</hi> the two Hoſts grew into a great league of loue &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together, but euer and anon when hee of <hi>London</hi> was about his buſineſſe, or out of the way, mine Hoſt of <hi>Walden</hi> was importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with his wife to make him a Cuckold: which the modeſt woman at her beſt opportunity told to her husband what a falſe friend hee was to him, for which he vows reuenge, and taking no notice at all what was paſt: The time came that mine Hoſt of <hi>Walden</hi> was for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; great healths, and much prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of loue there was at their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21212:35"/> parting: But this iniury ſtill ſticks in mine hoſt of <hi>Londons</hi> ſtomacke. A toy takes him in the head in the long vacation, he takes his horſe, &amp; rides purpoſely to ſee his old friend of <hi>Walden;</hi> and comming neare the Towne, he ſpurres ſomewhat hard, alights in the Inne yard, his horſe being all of a ſweat, he cals for an Oftler to walke him vp and downe; he was no ſooner diſmounted but he was eſpyed by his old friend and familiar acquaintance, who runnes to him, embraces him, and cals out his wife to bid him welcome: the woman appeares; This is mine hoſt (ſaith he) of <hi>London,</hi> which vſeth me with kindneſſe and reſpect, to whom I am ſo much bound, and whoſe health I haue drunke, and thou haſt pledg'd ſo often; now I pray thee <hi>Ioane</hi> with a kiſſe bid him welcome into the Countrey. The woman in great curteſie offers him her lips, whom he ſcornfully puts by: and I pray you good woman are
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21212:36"/> you wife to this man? yes, ſaid ſhee, for default of a better: but I intreat you foole not me ſaith hee, I came to viſit this my friend in kindneſſe, and not to be derided. Derided ſaith ſhe, why ſpeake you that, I am ſhee that hath laid by his ſide this twenty yeares: I that ſhe hath I can aſſure you, quoth mine hoſt of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den:</hi> But will you tell me that, quoth mine hoſt of <hi>London,</hi> of certainty I know this not to bee the woman you were wont to bring to my houſe to lodge, and lay with her Tearme by Tearme, I hope I know her if I ſee her againe: nay mine hoſt ſaith he, if you bee ſuch a kinde of fellow, here is no ſtaying for mee; at which words while the other ſtood halfe amazed, hee leapes vp into the ſaddle, and without mere pauſe ſpurres back as faſt as hee can, to <hi>London.</hi> Mine hoſt of <hi>Walden</hi> cals after him, but in vaine: the woman railes, he would excuſe it, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be heard: drunkard, and whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21212:36"/> are the beſt ſhee can afford him: the houſe is all in an vproare; nor could the man and wife euer be reconciled, notwithſtanding all his vowes, and oathes, with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of neighbours and friends, till mine hoſt of <hi>London,</hi> thinking himſelfe partly reuenged, ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand and ſeale, that it was but a meere trick put vpon him in requitall of a former iniury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>55. Two old Widowes.</head>
               <p>TWo old widowes ſitting ouer a Cup of Ale in a Winters night, entred into diſcourſe of their dead husbands, &amp; after the ripping vp of their good, and bad qualities, ſaith one of them to her maid, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee wench reach vs another light, for my husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, (God reſt his ſoule) aboue all things lou'd to ſee good lights about the houſe, God grant him light euerlaſting: and I pray you neighbour (ſaith the other) let
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21212:37"/> the maid lay on ſome more Coles, or ſtirre vp the fire, for my husband in his life time euer lou'd to ſee a good fire, God grant him fire euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>56. A Horſe-ſtealer.</head>
               <p>A Fellow for ſtealing of a horſe was apprehended, arraigned, conuicted, and executed: the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion being made, why this man was hanged, it was anſwered for ſtealing a horſe, Nay ſaith the other, I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you no ſuch matter, hee was hanged for being taken, for had he ſtolne an hundred and neuer beene taken, he might haue beene aliue at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>57. A Baker.</head>
               <p>ONe being called in queſtion before a Iuſtice for giuing a Baker ill language: now, ſaith the Iuſtice, my friend, what ſay you to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21212:37"/> this complaint? Truely ſir ſaid hee, the worſt words that euer I gaue him, was that I held him to bee as honeſt a man as euer liued by bread.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>58. A Coachman.</head>
               <p>A Mad fellow, a Coachman a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Towne being drunk, fell from the ſeat where he ſare, and the wheels running ouer him, brake one of his legs, the anguiſh of which droue him into a Feuer: but being well recouered of them both, hee had an humour to goe and proue all the prime Doctors of the Towne, and try whether by his water they could tell his profeſſion, or his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, or the diſeaſe that before had troubled him: he being then in perfect health, his water was carried to many, and all that ſaw it, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that hee that ſent it was a ſound man, but could proceed no further; therefore his opinion was, that all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21212:38"/> Phyſitians were fooles, and not one learned man amongſt them. This being told an ancient graue Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor that practiſed about the Citie by one of the Coachmans acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, by whom he had vnderſtood euery particular before related: he wrought with him to perſwade the Coachman to bring his water to him, which tooke effect: But in their iourney towards the Doctor, they drinking ſomewhat hard, the Coachma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carrying his vrinall emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, piſt it full, which his friend ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, fie, ſaith hee, carry not all this water along for ſhame, poure out halfe at leaſt, otherwiſe he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue we haue beene drinking; the Coachman was perſwaded, and did ſo. On they went, and whilſt the Coachman ſtaid below, his friend went vp to ſee if the Doctor were at leaſure, and told him all that paſt by the way: This done, the Patient is call'd vp, who preſents his Vrinal to the Doctor, with many a low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21212:38"/> outwardly, though ſcoffing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly. The Doctor he turnes, and toſſes the glaſſe, ſometimes chafing it againſt the fire, then againe holds it vp to the light: at laſt he breakes into theſe words, I perceiue by this water, that hee that made it was a Carter, or Carman. Truly (ſaith he) if it pleaſe your Worſhip, you come the neareſt of all the Doctors I haue tryed yet, and yet you are wide from the marke. Wilt thou tell mee that ſaith the Doctor, ſure I am he is one that gets his liuing by the whip. Therein you are right again anſwered the other: for to tell you true he was a Coachman. Very good ſaith the Doctor: now this Carter being drunke, fell from his Cart, and the wheele ran ouer him and brake his leg. You are right in all things ſir, if you would change the Cart, &amp; the Carter, into the Coach, &amp; Coachma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Interrupt me not, ſaith the Doctor; this Carter breaking his Leg, fell after into a dangerous Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21212:39"/> of which he is ſince recouered. Good your worſhip. Good your Worſhip, no more Carter, nor Cart, if you loue mee; for of my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he was a Coachman, and fell from his Coach. His Coach ſaith the Doctor, ſtill looking vpon the Vrin: I prethee truely reſolue me, is here all the water that was made? No indeed, ſaith the fellow, I pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out halfe by the way. Nay, I thought as much; then there went away the other two wheeles, ſaith the Doctor, for there cannot bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue two contained in this Vrinall. The Coachman admires his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, departs ſatisfied with his skill, ſaith, hee ſhall haue his cuſtome, with all his comrades; and vowed onely for his ſake, to ſpeake well of Doctors euer after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21212:39"/>
               <head>59. A Taylor.</head>
               <p>A Taylor bringing to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man a bill of extraordinary length, becauſe it included many reckonings, and altogether deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of preſent payment, becauſe the party had a preſent purpoſe to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell; the Gentleman demands what hee would bate him of the maine bill, and hee would pay him downe the reſt in ready money, ready caſh quoth the Taylor, being extaſide with the very thought, I will bate you ſaith he a full yard City meaſure and thats a handfull more, take it off in the middle, the top, or the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, either of all theſe three, chuſe you which.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>60. A Cheater.</head>
               <p>A Cheater hauing ſtolne a cup out of a Tauerne, and being purſude and taken in the ſtreets,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21212:40"/> there grew on the ſudden a great tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult of people, and a great conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was gathered together, a ciuill Gentleman paſſing, and ſeeing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come from thence that had bin at the vproare, demanded of him what was the reaſon of that throng, nothing ſaith hee, but that one hath gotten a cup too much, alas ſaith the other, nothing elſe, that may bee an honeſt mans fault, and mine as ſoone as anothers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>61. A handſome wench, and a Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>A Handſome wench for ſome ſuſpicious buſineſſe beeing brought before a Iuſtice ſomewhat late in the euening, and hee taking compaſſion of her becauſe ſhee was faire and ſeeming modeſt, wiſht the man that broght her before him to take her home, and lodge her that night, and he would heare the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more at large in the morning; Marry with all my heart, ſaith hee,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21212:40"/> Maſter Iuſtice, ſo you will but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my wife which is now at home to the Counter till the morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>62. A cleanly lye.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIll: Kempe</hi> by a miſchance was with a ſword run quite through the leg, a Country Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman comming to viſit him, asked him how he came by that miſcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, he told him, and withall, troth ſaith he, I receiued this hurt iuſt eight weekes ſince, and I haue line of it this quarter of a yeare, and neuer ſtirr'd out of my Chamber.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>63. Gentlemen at an Ordinary.</head>
               <p>CErtaine Gentlemen being in Game at an Ordinary, euery one complained of a filthy ranke ſmel that was amongſt them, which grew ſtill hotter and hotter in their Noſes: At length ſaith one of them ieſtingly, I pray you Gentlemen,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21212:41"/> which of you amongſt vs here v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to weare Socks? A Countrey Gentleman one of the company preſently anſwered, not I, I proteſt I neuer knew what belongs to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>64. Of a deafe Hoſteſſe.</head>
               <p>A Young Gentleman hauing a deafe hoſteſſe, vſed to put ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ieſts vpon her, and one day ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing invited diuers of his friends to dinner, and thinking to make them merry, taketh a glaſſe of wine, and maketh ſignes to the good old woman that he dranke to her, and ſaith, here Hoſteſſe, I will drinke to you, and to all your friends, namely the Baudes and Whores in <hi>Turne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bull</hi> ſtreet, to whom ſhe innocently ſaid, I thanke you Sir, euen with all my heart, I know you remember your Mother, your Aunt, and thoſe good Gentlewomen your ſiſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21212:41"/>
               <head>65. Of a Prentice.</head>
               <p>A Young Boy comming out of the Countrey, and being new bound Prentice, ſeeing my Lord Maiors ſhow, and wondring at the great pompe and ſtate hee rid in, I marry ſaith he, now I ſee what wee muſt all come too.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>66. A Spaniard and a Dutchman.</head>
               <p>A Spaniard and a Dutchman mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in an Inne, were appointed to bee bedfellowes, the Dutchman went firſt to bed, expecting the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who before hee vncas'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, takes out of his mouth a ſet of teeth, and wiping them laid them in a cleane napkin. The Dutchman being ſtill awake, began to wonder. In the meane time hee takes off his counterfeit haire, and ſhowes a head quite bald. The other ſtill obſerues him. Then he takes out an artificiall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21212:42"/> eye, wipes it, and layes it by the reſt. This began to ſtartle the other, who by this time had ſerued off his ſiluer Noſe, and then makes towards the bed: which the Dutchman ſeeing, leapes out of the bed, crying, the Deuill, the Deuill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>67. A great Lords entertainment.</head>
               <p>THe Maior of <hi>Exeter</hi> entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from his firſt <hi>Cales</hi> voyage; at dinner intreated my Lord to relate vnto him all the paſſage of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulting, and taking the Towne: Which my Lord hauing done at his intreaty: I marry ſaith he, this were braue indeed, if it were true. My Lord ſmiled at his ignorance, but ſaid little, but drunke to him. The Maior pledg'd his Lordſhip, and withal asked him how he liked the Wine? Who anſwered, it was very good. I but, ſaith Maſter Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, I haue a cup of Wine in my Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21212:42"/> &amp;c. I marry ſaith my Lord, I ſhould haue thought my ſelfe wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, indeed, if I might haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of that.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>68. An Empericke.</head>
               <p>AN Emperick that had but one cure for all diſeaſes, which was certaine Pils which he vſed to giue for all ſorts of maladies, by reaſon that ſome of his Patients were acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally cured: grew famous in the place where hee liued, amongſt the the ſimpler ſort: In ſo much that ſome of them held him for a learned Doctor: others for a cunning man. It hapned that a poore Countrey man, hauing his Cow ſtrayed from him, and giuing her out for loſt, heard the fame of this Artiſt; profers him money to helpe him to his Cow againe. Who anſwered, if he would haue any Pils, he could helpe him to them. Yes, with all my heart ſaith the poore man, if I
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21212:43"/> thought they would doe mee any good in this buſineſſe. The Artiſt ſels him Pils, and teacheth him how to take them; which hee preſently did, and bids him farewell. The man going homeward the Phyſicke began to worke with him: hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires himſelfe for modeſty ſake from the highway into a neigbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thicket; where as hee ſate, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his eye aſide, hee by chance ſaw his Cow grazing amongſt the buſhes; at which hee reioyced. The next day he returned to the City, to giue thankes, by whoſe report hee grew ten times more famous then before among the vulgar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>69. Of a Horſe.</head>
               <p>QVeene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe to Couentry, was met a diſtance from the Towne by the Maior and his Brethren, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to the City. There was a Water in the way, and Maſter Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21212:43"/> horſe would needes drinke; but his rider not ſuffering him, but cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing him in, the horſe kept ſuch a plunging in the water, that he daſht the Queene; who called to him, and asked him why hee did not let his Horſe drinke? Who anſwered, if it pleaſe your Grace, I was not ſo ill bred, as to ſuffer my Horſe to drinke before you Maieſties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>70. A young Citizen and his Wife.</head>
               <p>A Young Citizen and his wife being at dinner together, hee had earen Egs, and ſhee was feeding vpon Beefe; and finding her ſelfe ſomwhat drye: Sweet husband ſaith ſhee, I prethee drinke to mee, and I will pledge thee; thee after thine Egge, and I after mine Oxe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:21212:44"/>
               <head>71. Of Rape ſeed.</head>
               <p>A Hanſome young fellow hauing ſeene a Play at the <hi>Curtaine,</hi> comes to <hi>William Rowly</hi> after the Play was done, and intreated him if his leiſure ſerued, that hee might giue him a Pottle of Wine, to bee better acquainted with him. Hee thankt him, and told him if hee pleaſed to goe as farre as the Kings Head at Spittlegate, hee would as ſoone as he had made himſelfe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy follow him, and accept of his kindneſſe. He did ſo, but the Wine ſeeming tedious betwixt two, and the rather becauſe the young fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low could entertaine no diſcourſe, <hi>Rowly</hi> beckoned to an honeſt fellow ouer the way to come and keepe them company; who promiſed to be with them inſtantly. But not comming at the ſecond or third calling. At laſt he appeares in the roome, where <hi>William Rowly</hi> begins
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21212:44"/> to chide him becauſe he had ſtaid ſo long. Hee preſently craued par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and begins to excuſe himſelfe, that hee had beene abroad to buy Rape ſeed, and that he ſtaid to ſeed his birds. At the very word of Rape ſeed, the man roſe from the Table, with a changed countenance, being very much diſcontented, and ſaid, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rowly</hi> I came in curteſie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your acquaintance, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow the Wine vpon you, not thinking you would haue called this fellow vp to taunt mee ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, (they wondring what hee meant,) Hee proceeded. Tis true indeed, the laſt Seſſions I was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned at Newgate for a Rape: but I thanke God, I came off like an honeſt man, little thinking to bee twitted of it here. Both began to excuſe themſelues, as not knowing any ſuch thing, as well as they might. But he that gaue the offence, thinking the better to expreſſe his innocence; young Gentleman, ſaith
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21212:45"/> he, to expreſſe how farre I was from wronging of you, locke you here, as I haue Rape ſeed in one Pocket for one Bird, ſo here is Hempe ſeed on this ſide for another. At which word, Hempe ſeed, ſaith the young man, Why Villaine, doeſt thou thinke I haue deſerued hanging? and tooke vp the Pot to fling at his head, but his hand was ſtayed: and as errour and miſtake began the quarrell, ſo Wine ended it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>72. Of a Thatcher.</head>
               <p>A Thatcher being on the top of an houſe, one of the maides ſpeaks to him ſomewhat haſtily, and bids him come downe to break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, The fellow whether ouer-ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the newes, or what the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer was I know not, but his hands left their hold, and his feet ſlipt, and downe he came ſliding; which the wench ſeeing, cals aloud to him, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21212:45"/> ſaith, Gaffer, Gaffer, you need not make ſuch haſt, for breakfaſt is not ready.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>73. Of another Thatcher.</head>
               <p>ANother of the ſame trade, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at worke on the ridge of an high Barne, and all the Thatch looſe beneath him, his feet ſlipt from him, and ſtill as hee felt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe falling, catching vncertaine hold, as the Thatch faild him, he cryde, Lord helpe me, Lord bleſſe me, Lord preſerue mee: but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Eues, and beholding what a great diſtance it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and the ground; raps out a great oath, and ſayes, what a huge fall am I like to haue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21212:46"/>
               <head>74. Of an Oxe hide.</head>
               <p>A Scholler of the Vniuerſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad late in the Towne, comming by a Tanners houſe, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſtumble vpon a raw Oxe hyde that lay before his doore: and groping with his hand to know what it was, firſt hits vpon the hyde, and after vpon the hornes, vpon which he had this conceit:
<q>
                     <l>Te toga dat noſtrum, te dant tua cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua Ciuem.</l>
                  </q> In Engliſh thus;
<q>
                     <l>Thou ſhouldſt be Scholler by thy Gown,</l>
                     <l>But by thy Hornes one of the Towne.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>75. Three Surgeons.</head>
               <p>THree Surgeons in their owne Countries were equally fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and all at one time: the one in <hi>England,</hi> another in <hi>Ireland,</hi> a third in <hi>Wales.</hi> Now as all men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21212:46"/> enquire after ſuch as are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in their owne quality: ſo each of theſe by rumour hauing heard much of the others excellencie: They had great deſire to ſee one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and were all in the ſame thought. The Iriſhman comes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to enquire after both, or either iuſt at the ſame time when the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman was iourneying towards <hi>Wales,</hi> and the Welchman towards <hi>England.</hi> Theſe three by accident met in one Inne, all ſtrangers one to another. Motion was made by the Hoſteſſe, in regard they were ſingle men, that they might Sup together: It was accepted of. After ſupper they grew in diſcourſe of their owne Art. The Iriſhman extols one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in <hi>England,</hi> another in <hi>Wales:</hi> The <hi>Welchman</hi> is as liberall in the praiſe of an Engliſhman, and an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhman: The Engliſhman is as free in commending the other. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome circumſtance, they finde themſelues to be the ſame. Many
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21212:47"/> enterchanging of curteſie paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them: and the Table being drawne, they concluded all to lye in one Chamber. A great fire being made, and ſome healths paſſing round: at length ſaith the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, we are all famous for our Art practiſed vpon others; being ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately met, it were not much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe if we practiſed ſomething vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues. The others as ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to make triall of their skill, gaue conſent to the motion. The Engliſhman preſently cals for a cleane wooden diſh; and hauing commanded the hoſteſſe to leaue the Chamber, takes his inciſion Knife, and opens himſelfe before the fire, rips vp his belly, takes out his ſtomack or Paunch, and caſts it into the wooden diſh: then bindes vp his body, as his Art taught him, without any trouble of colour or countenance. Which they ſeeing, notwithſtanding cheered him vp, and asked him how hee did. Hee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21212:47"/> anſwered, (I thanke God) neuer better, onely for the preſent hee wanted a ſtomack. They applaud his cunning. Then the Iriſhman loath to be exceeded in his Art, with his knife takes out one of his eyes, with the ſtrings, and without ſhew of feare or ſigne of paine, cloſeth vp the place with a plaiſter, and layes it to the Engliſhmans Paunch in the wooden Platter. Which the Welch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man obſeruing, and ſcorning to bee vnderualued in his Art, leapes to his ſword, and takes it in the leſt hand, and cuts off the right, ſtancheth the blood, bindes vp the wound, &amp; caſts it to the reſt, as little moued as the other. This done, they deliuer vp the paunch, the eye, and the hand to be kept ſafe, and deliuered backe to them in the morning. And then to bed they goe. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſſe layes theſe things in the wet Larder: but her daughter forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to locke the doore; about break of day in comes a Cow, and eates vp
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21212:48"/> all in the Tray. The hoſteſſe riſing betimes in the morning, going to ſee her charge, finds all deuoured, and no ſigne of any thing remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſhee growes into a great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie for her gueſts, grieuing that ſhe ſhould bee the cauſe of their deaths: Which her daughter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-hearing, comforts her mother thus. To ſatisfie your gueſts in ſhew, and to auoid the law, we haue incurd by our negligence. Firſt for the Engliſhman, they ſay the paunch of an Hog, or a Sow is iuſt like the ſtomack of a man, or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: Our Sow is fat, and to be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſhortly, cut her throat now, her fleſh will be neuer a whit the worſe, and lay her Paunch in the place of the other, this was no ſooner adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then put in practiſe. But now ſaith the hoſteſſe, how ſhall we doe for the Iriſhmans eye? Oh mother ſaith the Girle, looke but vpon our gray eyed Cat, and ſhee hath hath ſuch eyes as he hath for all the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21212:48"/> world. The mother apprehends, the Cat is taken, and ſuffers, and her eye caſt into the tray in ſtead of the Iriſhmans. That done, what ſhift (ſaith mine hoſteſſe) ſhall we make for the <hi>Welchmans</hi> hand? Oh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith the Girle, but yeſterday a theefe ſuffered, and hangs ſtill vpon the Gallowes: ſend quickly to the place, and cut off his hand, and lay it in the place of the <hi>Welchmans.</hi> Al is done, the Surgeons call, the Tray is carried vp, and (as they thinke) euery thing accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated in his owne place. The Engliſhman cloſeth vp his ſtomack: the Iriſhman puts in his eye: the Welchman faſtens on his hand, and euery of them in outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſeemes whole, and ſound. And being ready to take horſe, and part, ſaith one of them; theſe cures ſeeme currant for the preſent, but whether they bee ſetled, or perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, may bee a queſtion: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hold it fit that euery one of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21212:49"/> vs trauell about our moſt neceſſary affaires, and meet here againe in the ſame place this day month, to giue account of our cures. It is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: the day comes: the Artiſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare according to promiſe. They firſt aske the Engliſhman concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſtate of his body? Who anwered, hee was neuer in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter health, nor euer had ſo great a ſtomack; for now no meat can come amiſſe to him, raw, or roaſted: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he had much adoe to keepe his Noſe out of euery ſwilling Tub: Nay, hee cannot ſee a young Child turne his backſide to the wal, but he had a great minde to be doing with it. They queſtion next the Iriſhman of his health: who anſwers, that hee feeles himſelfe well, ſauing that he feeles ſome defect in that one eye, for when the one is ſhut, and aſleep, the other is open and awake. Beſides, if at midnight he hear a Rat or a Mouſe ſtirring, hee could not contain himſelfe from ſtepping out
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21212:49"/> of bed, breaking his Shins ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that they were neuer without plaiſters. They queſtion the Welchman laſt, he proteſts that he is well, and in health, and that in his owne nature he is both of good condition, and conuerſation, but euer ſince the reioyning of that hand, he hath much adoe from ſtealing whatſoeuer ſtands in his way, and from keeping it out of the next mans Pocket.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>76. Of Bucanon.</head>
               <p>THe famous Poet <hi>Bucanon</hi> in his trauels was taken hold of by ſome of the Popes Inquiſitors, who by his free writing, ſuſpected his religion, but hee to acquit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, wrote vnto his holineſſe this Dyſticon:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21212:50"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Laus tua non tua fraus, virtus non copia rerum,</l>
                     <l>Scandere te fecit hoc decus eximium.</l>
                  </q> Which thus I paraphraſe.
<q>
                     <l>Thy praiſe not fraud, thy vertue, not thy ſtore,</l>
                     <l>Made thee to climbe that height which we adore.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For which <hi>Encomium</hi> he was ſet at liberty, and being got out of the <hi>Popes</hi> iuriſdiction, he ſent to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and deſired according to his owne true meaning, to reade the ſelfeſame verſes backward which were theſe:
<q>
                     <l>Eximium decus hoc fecit te ſcandere rerum</l>
                     <l>Copia, non virtus, fraus tua, non tua laus.</l>
                  </q> Thus Engliſhed:
<q>
                     <l>The height which we adore, what made thee climbe?</l>
                     <l>Not vertue, nor thy worth, rather thy crime.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:21212:50"/>
               <head>77. An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer dying.</head>
               <p>A Great Vſurer hauing purchaſed a mighty eſtate, as all men are mortall, ſo the time came when hee muſt leaue the world: and lying vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his deathbed, the Doctors, and Phyſitians hauing giuen him ouer, a Reuerend Diuine was ſent to comfort him; who telling him of many comforts for his ſoules health, amongſt other things, ſaid, hee had beene a great purchaſer vpon earth, but now he muſt ſtudy for another purchaſe, which was the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. He turning vpon the other ſide, at the hearing of the word purchaſe, anſwered, I will not giue more then according to fifteene yeares for the purchaſe, and ſo died. This Gentleman preaching at his funerall, in the concluſion of his Sermon, ſaid onely thus, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and dearely beloued, it is now expected, that ſhould ſpeake
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21212:51"/> ſomething concerning our brother here deceaſed: I will end it in few words, namely theſe: How he liued you know, how hee dyed I know, and where his ſoule is now, God Almighty knowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>78. A pariſh Clarke.</head>
               <p>AN honeſt man, a Pariſh Clarke, and a freeman of <hi>London,</hi> by trade a Skinner, being by the Preacher, before hee went into the Pulpit, (becauſe he found himſelfe at the preſent not very well) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to ſing a Pſalme of ſome length: I will ſaid he, and ſaid aloud thus: I intreat you good people ſing Lamentation of a Skinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21212:51"/>
               <head>79. Two ſiſters.</head>
               <p>TWo ſiſters, the one being excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faire, the other extreame blacke: It ſo fortuned, the one had Suters, the other had none. The faire one meeting with a Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart of hers in a Garden, to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> her cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber window was a proſpect, they grew ſo wantonly familiar, that it was moſt vndecent, and vnſeemely; the blacke ſiſter finding the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers chamber open, and eſpying all which had paſt; with her diamond writes, <hi>Te tam formoſam non decet eſſe leuem,</hi> and hauing done this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyes her ſelfe out of the roome. Their dalliance being ended, the faire ſiſter returning to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and finding no body there, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies what was writ in the window, and finding it to be her ſiſters oha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacter, thus ſubſcribes, <hi>Te non formo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam non valet eſſe leuem,</hi> which I thus interpret, the firſt:</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:21212:52"/>
               <q>So faire and light doe not agree.</q>
               <p>The anſwere:</p>
               <q>Were you as faire ſuch would you be.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>80. Wiſhers, and woulders.</head>
               <p>ONe deſiring a Scholler to turne the old ancient Engliſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe into Latine, Wiſhers and Woulders were neuer good houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders. That I will preſently, ſaith the Scholler thus, <hi>Oh ſi, oh ſi, otioſi.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>81. Barbarous Latine.</head>
               <p>ONe thinking with barbarous latine to put down a Scholler, came and ſaluted him in theſe words, <hi>Ars tufons,</hi> art thou well? To whom he preſently anſwered in the others garbe, <hi>Aſinus fons, Aſinus tu;</hi> that is, <hi>As well as thou.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:21212:52"/>
               <head>81. A Gentleman to a Lady.</head>
               <p>A Witty conceited Gentleman, that when he came among La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, would often bolt out a phreſe of Latine; one of them, that thought her ſelfe the moſt witty amongſt the reſt, ſaid vnto him, Sir you are ever and anon out with your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, which wee Gentlewomen vnderſtand not, therefore are afraid leſt you ſhould play vpon vs: But for mine one part, I perſwade my ſelfe that if you ſpeake but two words, if one of them bee good, the other is naught. I, ſaith he, Madam; what ſay you then of theſe two words, <hi>bona mulier,</hi> good woman? Well ſaith ſhee, <hi>bona</hi> may bee good, but if <hi>mulier</hi> be not naught, then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer truſt me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21212:53"/>
               <head>83. Two hyring one horſe.</head>
               <p>TWo fellowes purpoſing a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hyred a horſe betwixt them to ride by turnes: The one laid downe halfe the hire, and cals to his partner for the other halfe, which he willingly disburſt. Which done, ſaith he, marke the conditions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs, which are theſe: when I ride, then you ſhall goe a foore, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you go on foot the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal ride. This is the bargaine, will you ſtand to it? Yes, with all my heart ſaith the other. So the firſt got vp, rod the whole iourney, and left the other to come on foot after him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>84. A Gentleman and a Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman hyred a Horſe in <hi>Smithfield</hi> to ride a iourney twenty miles beyond <hi>Yorke,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing paid the Horſecourſer his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21212:53"/> hee deſired to know of him whether the horſe would ſerue him his iourney, or no? to whom the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low anſwered, that without doubt he would, if he would but obſerue three things, the Gentleman asking what they were, The firſt is ſaith he, you muſt meat him well. Feare not ſaith the other, for I look to my horſe, as to my ſelfe. The ſecond is, you muſt not ride him vp hill nor downe hill. Well ſaith hee, I muſt ſpare him to eaſe my ſelfe. Now what is the third, marry ſaith he, driue him before you in all the euen way you come in, and if hee ſerue not your iourny as wel as any horſe in England, truſt me no more. Thus was the poore Gentleman not onely iaded, but mockt for his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:21212:54"/>
               <head>85. A man buying a Cow.</head>
               <p>A Certaine man came into the Market, to buy a Cow, and bought one: when he had paid for her he deſired to know what faults ſhe had. Now the Cow could not endure any to ſtand iuſt before her: ſo the ſeller ſpoke to the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſtand iuſt before her, and he ſhould ſee all her faults at once: which he did: but no ſooner was hee iuſt before her, thinking to ſee ſome egregious fault in her, and alas he felt it, for ſhee ran at him, and threw him along in the dirt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:21212:54"/>
               <head>86. A Doctor and a Lady.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Butler</hi> being very angry with a Lady, call'd her whore: ſhe makes a grieuous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint vpon him; in ſo much, that partly by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, partly by intreaty, hee was forced to recant his words before a competent company, ſuch as for her beſt ſatisfaction ſhee would make choyſe of. The time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted came, wherein he recanted in theſe words:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Madam I call'd you whore, tis true. and to ſpeake otherwiſe, I ſhould lye.</l>
                  <l>I come to giue you ſatisfaction, I am ſorry.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Vpon theſe termes grew a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reconcilement betweene them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:21212:55"/>
               <head>87. An Epitaph.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman hauing loſt a deare friend of his, and willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome monument vpon him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, comes to a Scholler, deſiring him to make him a Epitaph for that purpoſe, he told him withall his heare, then hee demanded, what ſpeciall vertues his friend had when he liu'd, that in his death hee might commend them to poſteritie, who anſwered hee never tooke notice of any particular vertues; he askt him then what noted vices he was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, hee told him againe not any that he knew, but that he was a good honeſt morall man, and more hee could not ſpeake for him: the third queſtion was, he demanded how old he was, when hee departed his life, he anſwered he was iuſt ſixty yeares of age, vpon which hee writ this Epitaph:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Here lyes a man was borne and cride,</l>
                  <l>Told threeſcore yeares, fell ſick, &amp; dide.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:21212:55"/>
               <head>88. Pope Alexander VI.</head>
               <p>POpe <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the Papacy rather by force then the conſort of a free elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, one comming to read his title, which was <hi>Alexander Papa</hi> VI. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, read <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Papa vi. Alexander</hi> Pope by force.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>89. Pictures hang'd.</head>
               <p>A Fantaſticke Gentleman having beſpoken diuers Pictures to furniſh a Gallery, the picturer bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them home, hee was diſpoſing them in their ſeuerall places, here ſaith he, hang this, there that, and there that, but here will be hanged my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:21212:56"/>
               <head>90. Comming of the Spaniards.</head>
               <p>ONe comming fearfully into a company of Gentlemen, told them hee could tell them moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full newes, they asked him what it was, Marry ſaith he, it is publikely rumored that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will bee here before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> Tuſh let not that trouble you ſaith one of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, I will neuer beleeue it, for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> kill no fleſh in Lent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>91. A father and his daughter.</head>
               <p>A Father being ſuſpicious of his daughter, and of a young man that was a ſurer to her, whom hee did no way affect, tooke his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſchooling, and made her vow vnto him never more to come into his company without asking leaue, vpon a time her father ſitting by the fire, and ſhe hauing notice giuen her that her friend was at the doore to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21212:56"/> ſpeake with her, ſhee made an exuſe to reach ſomething behind her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as ſhe ſtooped, ſaid father, by your leaue: marry good leaue haue you daughter ſaith he, which was no ſooner ſpoke, but out ſhee went to her ſweet heart, and ſaw her father no more till ſhee came home a maried wife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>92. A letter writ out of the Countrey.</head>
               <p>A Countryman writ a Letter to a friend of his at <hi>London</hi> after this manner: After my hearty commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, hoping in God that you are in good health, as I am at the making hereof, &amp;c. theſe are to let you vnderſtand that at this preſent I am extremly ſicke, and much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a quartaine ague, in ſo much that there is ſmall hopes ever to be mine owne man againe: And for ſuch a man that hath done mee moſt violent and dangerous wrongs I doe forgive him with all my heart
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21212:57"/> and ſoule: but if it ſhall pleaſe God I may recouer this ſickneſſe, I will be revenged of him to the utmoſt of my power, though it coſt mee all that euer I am or ſhall be worth, thus being loath to trouble you any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I remaine, and ceaſe ever to be your louing friend,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>93. A lye retorted.</head>
               <p>ONe hearing another in the company tell a lye, at leaſt an extreme impoſſibility, all condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it for a thing that had no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of truth: no ſaith one, I can tell you as ſtrange a wonder as that, walking the other day over the fields, and plowed lands, it was my fortune to caſt mine eye vpon a Hare that was ſitting, hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at that time in mine hand, and being deſirous to kil her ſitting, ſtill fixing my eyes vpon her, I ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to take vp a clod or ſtone to fling at her, &amp; beat out her braines,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21212:57"/> and in that thought ſtooping to catch vp ſomething, I faſtned vpon another hare that ſate there formed, caſt her from me, and hit the other as ſhee was riſing, and brake both their necks, and carried them home to ſupper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>94. A Scotchman and his Miſtris.</head>
               <p>A Scotchman in the beginning of the <hi>ſpring,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarce one flowre was ſeene to bud out of the earth, by chance walking to take the ayre, caſt his eye vpon a Primroſe fairly blowne, and being about to plucke it, he began to conſider with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, how much more acceptable would this be to my Lady, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, if for the rareneſſe thereof ſhe gathered it with her owne faire hand, and in this thought he purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call her from her Chamber, and bring her to the place, but fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſt any one in his abſence ſhould find it out, hee thought it the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21212:58"/> ſafeſt way to couer it with his hat, ſo he did, and goes withall ſpeed to his Ladies Chamber, in this <hi>interim</hi> one comming by that way, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he before obſerued him or no, I know not) but remouing the hatt to ſee what was vnder it, eſpies the flower, and crops it, and in the ſame place he left a Roſe of a worſe ſmell behind him, couers it with the hat, and conueighes himſelfe quite out of ſight, preſently after comes the Scotchman leading his Lady by the arme, tells her after many comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the rareneſſe of the flowre, and of his great fortune to finde it, and how much more precious ſhee ſhould make it by plucking it in her owne perſon. Why where is this dainty flower ſaith ſhe you ſo much praiſe and ſpeake of. Why here ſweet Lady ſaith he couered with this my Beauer, and with curioſity remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, diſcouers the thing I ſpake of, ſtill ſmelling, and therefore more offenſiue to the ſmell, the Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:21212:58"/> bluſhes, the Lady railes, what he then thought, or how her dainty noſe tooke it, I leaue it to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders conſiderations:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So dainty was her noſe? and ſhee not ſmell</l>
                  <l>That ſent before ſhe came ſo neere? and tell</l>
                  <l>The Scotchman that for recreation</l>
                  <l>She walkt with him, ſo far tis Ladies faſhion,</l>
                  <l>But flowers ſhe'de haue none, ſo ſoone this yeare,</l>
                  <l>So might ſhe have ie'rde him, and not he her.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>95. Of a Gentleman that was the firſt of his houſe.</head>
               <p>ONe Gentleman obiecting to another, that he was the firſt of his houſe, the other anſwered that is my honour that thou vpbraideſt me with, but bee it thy diſhonour that thou art likely to bee the laſt of thine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:21212:59"/>
               <head>96. An Empericke and his man.</head>
               <p>A Phyſician and his man riding a long, they perceiued a diſtance off, a great confluence of people aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: the maſter deſirous to know the reaſon thereof, ſends his ſervant to know the cauſe, and to giue him notice, which the fellow did, &amp; gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopping backe with all the ſpeed he could, deſires his maſter if hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his life, to put ſpurs to his horſe, and to prouide for his preſent ſafety otherwiſe he was but a loſt man: at which the Phyſitian amazed, deſired likewiſe to know the reaſon of that, his man replied, Sir, the reaſon of this meeting is to behold the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one that hath killed a man, now if he were condemned for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of one, what danger are you in, that to my knowledge haue beene the death of halfe a hundred at the leaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:21212:59"/>
               <head>97. Two Country Fellowes.</head>
               <p>Two Country fellowes meeting at an Aſſizes in the Countrey, one askt the other what newes, and how many were condemned to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, the other anſwered, This hath beene the ſtrangeſt Seſſions that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in my time, I haue not knowne the like, for there is no exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution at all, and is it not worthy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that ſo many Iuſtices ſhould ſit on the Bench, and not one thought worthy to be hanged?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>98. A Churchman in his Inne.</head>
               <p>A Churchman being in his Inn, and arguing with an high voice, fie quoth his curious hoſteſſe, Sir, why doe you talke ſo lowd? mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſweet Hoſteſſe ſaith he, becauſe I am alowd to talke, and ſo are not you without the conſent of your husband.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21212:60"/>
               <head>99. An Engliſh Gentleman in France.</head>
               <p>AN Engliſh Gentleman being in <hi>France,</hi> and hauing exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe in a dancing ſchoole, had put off his pumps, and wiping himſelfe with a dry towell, was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to depart, at which time enters a French <hi>Mounſier,</hi> and intreated him to put on his pumps againe that he might ſee him practiſe, the other excuſed it by reaſon of his wearines, and that by too much heating his body, hee might endanger a ſurfet, but the <hi>Mounſier</hi> from intreaty grew to importunity, from impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunacy to threats, and withall ſeeing his ſword lye a diſtance from him drawes it, and ſweares that if he will not preſently ſatisfie him in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, hee will runne him through: the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeing at what advantage he had him, yeelds to the preſent neceſſity, dances out his Galliard, and gives him as much
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:21212:60"/> content as he can deſire, but having ended, made himſelfe ready, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered his ſword, comming cloſe to the Mounſier, hee tells him, that if he be a gentleman, he muſt ſatisfie him for this affront, and either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that hee had done him a manifeſt wrong, or decide the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference by the ſword: the other ſeeing how neere it toucht his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, told him hee would giue him meeting to his deſire: the place, and houre was appointed, their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons agreed vpon, and their length taken: The morning came, and ſingly without Seconds they met and drew, the Engliſhman preſently drawes a caſe of Piſtols, and bids the <hi>Mounſier</hi> dance, I and to what tune he would either ſing or whiſtle: the other taxes him of diſhonorable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, but he is obſtinate, and ſweares he will ſhoot him if he will not dance: then the French man layes downe his armes, and footes it with all the curioſitie hee could,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21212:61"/> hihich done, the Engliſh man tells tem now they are vpon equall wrmes, gives him leaue to reſt and breathe, and hauing made himſelfe ſport ſufficiently, fought with him, and had the better of the Duell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>100. A Gentlemen and a Conſtable.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman comming late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conſtable, thinking to haue paſt the watch, hee was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before the lanthorne, and very ſtrictly demanded who he was, and whom he ſerued, hee anſwered, he was as they ſaw a man, and that hee ſerued God. I, ſay you ſo, ſaith the Conſtable, then cary him to the Compter, if you ſerue no body elſe: yes Sir replyed the Gentleman, I ſerue my Lord Chamberlaine. Say you ſo ſaith the Conſtable, why did you not tell mee ſo before? Marry ſaith the Gentleman, becauſe I had thought you had loued God better then my Lord Chamberlaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:21212:61"/>
               <head>101. A rich man and a poore.</head>
               <p>ONe aske this queſtion, What was that, that the poore man throwes away, and the rich man puts vp in his pocket? It was anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when the rich man blowes his noſe in a hankercher.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>102. A ſleepy drawer.</head>
               <p>A Drawer ſleeping vnder the Pulpit, the Preacher beat his deske ſo hard, that hee being ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly awaked, ſtart vp, and cryed openly in the Church, Anon, Anon Sir.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>103. A famous Painter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANgelo</hi> a moſt famous painter in <hi>Rome,</hi> wrought all thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous peeces, or the moſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are now to be ſeene in S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, and working privately
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21212:62"/> with a curtaine before him, as not willing his tables ſhould bee ſeene till his <hi>nouiſsima manus</hi> had beene vpon them, and that they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and perfect, being at that time about the reſurrection and laſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where the Elect were of one ſide, and the reprobate of the other, he had obſerued a Prieſt who would be ſtill prying into his worke, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bee reuenged on him, hee thought no more fit occaſion or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity then to draw his face to the life amongſt the damned, which he did with ſuch art and curioſitie, that when his worke came to bee ſeene, and made publike, not any that knew the Prieſt, but could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue, it perſonated him; for which hee grew to bee a deriſion or by-word among the people, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they would ſay to his face, that he was in <hi>Angeloes</hi> hell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: for which hee made a great complaint to the Clergy, at length petitioned to the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21212:62"/> his face might be taken from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and ſome put into the place: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Pope</hi> gaue anſwer, that hee muſt neceſſarily excuſe him in that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for true it was, that if <hi>Angelo</hi> had put him into purgatory, he then had power in himſelfe, to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed him thence, but ſeeing it was into hell, it was beyond his iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for <hi>ex inferis nulla redemptio,</hi> out of hell there is no redemption.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>104. Of giuing away Deere.</head>
               <p>A Priuate Gentleman of this Kingdome hauing a walke in the Forreſt, was complained on to King <hi>Iames,</hi> that hee had in one yeare giuen away aboue 60 heads of Deere, at the leaſt, at which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty being grieuouſly incenſed, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him before him, and askt him whether that were true that was reported of him, and told him of the complaint which was made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: to whom hee anſwered
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:21212:63"/> that it was moſt true, that within ſuch a time hee had giuen away as many: at which the King being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged he ſwore hee would haue him hanged for it: but hee beſeecht his Maieſtie to heare him fully: True it is ſaith he, that I haue giuen away ſo many to ſuch friends of mine that were ſutors to me for Veniſon; but if it come to bee proued that I haue deliuered any one of them, I ſhall then ſubmit my ſelfe to vndergoe your highneſſes moſt heauie diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, with which anſwer the King was appeaſed, and he acquitted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>105. The King a hunting.</head>
               <p>THe King being one day a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and pleaſing to retire him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to repaſt, leaned, or rather ſate vpon the ſame Gentleman, being fat and corpulent, ſomewhat to his diſeaſe, who boldly ſpoke to the King in theſe words; I doe beſeech your Maieſty, leane not too hard vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:21212:63"/> your cuſhion, leaſt you make the feathers tofly out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>106. Of choughing in ones graue.</head>
               <p>A Maſter of Art in one of the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities, hauing acted in a Tragedy, and his body lying ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead on the Stage, for the time was not yet come that hee ſhould be taken away, a paſſion tooke him that he was forced to cough ſo loud that it was perceiued by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall auditory, at which many of them falling into a laughter, hee riſing vp excuſed it thus: you may ſee Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen what it is to drinke in ones porridge, for they ſhall cough in their graue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>107. A Gentleman in diſgrace.</head>
               <p>A Worthy Gentleman, and a good Scholler had beene long in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the reaſon I know not, nor am willing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:21212:64"/> to examine, but he made meanes to one that was then in great fauour at Court, to bring him into fauor with her Maieſtie, which he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, and perſwaded the Queene to giue admittance of him into her preſence. The time was come, and the other brought him, where and when ſhee expected him: who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing done his duty with all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion that a ſubiect might; The Queene ſaith, I vnderſtand you are a great ſcholler, ſhall I aske you one queſtion? Any thing Madam ſaith he that lies within the compaſſe of mine vnderſtanding to reſolue you; then I pray you ſaith ſhe, how many vowells be there? Madam ſaith he, it is a queſtion that every ſchoole boy can reſolue you, but ſince you would be anſwered from me, there be fiue: fiue ſaith ſhe? but I pray you of theſe fiue, which may wee beſt ſpare? Not any of them Madam ſaith he, without corrupting of our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dialect. Yes replyed ſhe, I can tell
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:21212:64"/> you, for of them all we can (for our owne part) beſt ſpare <hi>u</hi> or you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>108. A ſimple Conſtable.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman walking late, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there to be a ſimple Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that had the watch that night, giuing him ſome peremptory termes, there was no way with him but to priſon he muſt, at length the Gentleman came vp cloſe to him, and bid him commit him if hee durſt. Why ſaith he, what may I call your name, that I who preſent the Kings perſon may not commit? Saith the Gentleman, my name is Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and neither by Gods Lawes nor mans ought you to commit mee: which one of the wiſeſt of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hearing, let him goe Maſter Conſtable ſaith he, let him goe, for if your wife ſhould heare that you had committed Adultery in your watch it might bee an euerlaſting breach of loue betwixt you. Vpon
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21212:65"/> this the conſtable was appeaſed, and the Gentleman went quietly to his lodging.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>109. The twelue ſignes of vſury.</head>
               <p>ONe being deſirous to know what twelue ſeverall Nations neereſt reſembled the 12. moneths, hauing their ſeuerall influences from them, was by one that ſtood by in Diſticks thus anſwered.</p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aquarius</hi> bids the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> at home tary,</l>
                  <l>And vſe baths, furres, and fires in Ianuary.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Piſces</hi> in February bids keepe warme,</l>
                  <l>Leſt haile, raine, ſnow, may doe the <hi>Lopland</hi> harme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <l>March of <hi>Mars</hi> ſauours, <hi>Aries</hi> the Commander,</l>
                  <l>To him belongs the warlike. <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <l>Aprill hath correſpondence to the <hi>French,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:21212:65"/>
                  <l>And <hi>Tau rus</hi> tells vs that he loves a wench.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <l>In <hi>Gemini</hi> the <hi>Italian</hi> loues to play,</l>
                  <l>And therefore he is like the Month of May.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <l>The Month of Iune is gouerned by the <hi>Crab,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> hot, and hee muſt haue a drab.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <l>In Iuly the bright Sunne in <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> ſwayes,</l>
                  <l>The parched <hi>Moores</hi> are tanned by his rayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leo</hi> in Auguſt reines, the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> then,</l>
                  <l>Though naked may bee counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <l>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> the <hi>Goat</hi> inuites as I remember,</l>
                  <l>To challenge to himſelfe the Month September.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <l>The <hi>Scorpion</hi> ripens harveſt in October,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Germane</hi> claimes that month, though ſeldome ſober.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:21212:66"/>
                  <l>The <hi>Auſtrian</hi> who his ſhape doth neuer vary,</l>
                  <l>Nouember claimes, ſwayd by the <hi>Sagittary.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <l>Vpon th' Hungarian <hi>Aquarius</hi> powres</l>
                  <l>Many full pots, filt by December ſhowers.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>110. One preaching againſt vſury.</head>
               <p>ONe preaching viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly againſt vſury, was by one that was knowne to bee a great money ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the ſame day inuited to dinner, but becauſe hee had ſo netled him and all of his profeſſion in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, he was at the firſt motion (fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome violence to bee offered to to his perſon) reſolved not to goe, but vpon conſideration, truſting to the priuiledge of his Cote, he bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went, and was exceeding wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, the Table being taken away the gueſts either diſperſed, or in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, the vſurer takes the Preacher
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:21212:66"/> aſide, puts ten peeces in his hand and thankes him kindly for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: the other wondring at his bounty, demanded of him the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof, for ſaid he, I was afraid I had much offended in being ſo bitter againſt thoſe two damnable crimes of oppreſſion and vſury. The other anſwered, I proteſt you were ſo farre from offence to mee ward, that you gaue mee much content, and I would intreat you to amplifie that Text, and in all your ſermons to inueigh againſt it ſtill. The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher asking his reaſon, I hope it may ſo edifie, and prevaile with ſome that they will quite giue it ouer, and ſo by that meanes, I and ſome others of my owne reſolution, may put out our money to our profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>111. Of a tall Gentleman, and a little Taylor.</head>
               <p>A Little low Taylor working to a tall Fantaſticke Gentleman,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:21212:67"/> had pleaſed him in all things, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that he neuer made his coller high enough, and beſpeaking a new ſuite, charged him to button him vp before two or three buttons more then ordinary. The Taylor willing to giue him all content, did accordingly: brought it home, and ſee it put on; and hauing buttond him to the height, it made him hold vp his chin, ſo that hee could ſcarce ſee any thing ſaue the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Saith the Taylor, haue I plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your worſhip now? Oh very well ſaith the Gentleman, this is as I would haue it. Reach me vp thy bill, and put thy hand into my other hoſe, there is my purſe, and tell out thy money. The Taylor did ſo, and told him he was ſatisfied. I am glad of it, ſaith the Gentleman, and not able to hold downe his head, Reach me thine hand honeſt friend, ſaith he, and now farewell, for I feare I ſhall neuer ſee thee againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:21212:67"/>
               <head>112. Two Gentlemen falling out.</head>
               <p>TWo young gentlemen falling out in a Tauerne ouer night, promiſed to meet in the field the next morning, and did ſo; but vpon cold blood diſtruſting their valours, they began to parle: at length it was concluded betwixt them, that in regard their going out was taken notice of by other gentlemen, and if no blood were drawne betwixt them, it might redound to both their diſparagement, to giue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſome ſleight hurt, or ſcratch ſuch a place, where they could beſt endure it: and ſo drew cuts who ſhould giue the firſt wound, and the other to appoint the place. Saith he who was the firſt patient, giue mee a little prick in the Arme: I will ſaith the other, and ran his Arme quite through. The other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſowre faces, at the ſmart ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now ſaith hee, ſtand me, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:21212:68"/> ſhew me where I ſhall hit you? But he that was vntoucht, perceiuing whom he had before wounded, to bee ſcarce able to hold his ſword, ſtands vpon his guard, and tels him he lay faire and open to him, bids him hit him where he could, and ſo came off boaſting &amp; bragging to his friends, how he had got the better of the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>113. A Drunkard.</head>
               <p>A Drunkard lying in the ſtreet, and not able to helpe himſelfe: a gentleman walking late without a light, ſtumbled at him, but by good fortune recouered himſelfe, &amp; perceiuing what had line in the way, I haue ſtumbled at a ſtraw, ſaith he, and leaped ouer a blocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:21212:68"/>
               <head>114. A Maſter of a ſhip.</head>
               <p>THere was one whoſe name was <hi>Man,</hi> and hee was Maſter of a ſhip, which was call'd the Moone: who was at Sea, and had beene in great familiaritie with a Sailers wife in <hi>Ratcliffe.</hi> In his abſence her husband finding her to bee a light huſwife: but not knowing of the former, charged her with a young Seafaring man, with whom ſhee had beene often at priuate meeting in company, and that very ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, in ſo much that he vrged her to tell him vpon her ſaluation, what in that kinde had paſſed betwixt them. The woman to giue his iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie ſatisfaction, fell downe vpon her knees, and wiſht ſome heauy fate might fall vpon her, if ſhe knew more by that party, then by the man in the Moone, at which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation the husband was ſatisfied, and as it is ſaid neuer iealous of her after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:21212:69"/>
               <head>115. A Gormandizer.</head>
               <p>A Gorma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dizing fellow proteſting to a friend of his that hee loued him as well as hee loued his ſoule. I thanke you ſir (ſaid he) with al my heart; but I had rather you loued me as well as you loue your body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>A Welch Reader.</head>
               <p>A Welchman reading the chapter of the Genealogie, where <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> begat <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> begat <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> ere he came to the midſt hee found the names ſo difficult, that he broke off in theſe words, and ſo they begat one another till they came to the end of the Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:21212:69"/>
               <head>117. A Biſhop and a Gentleman.</head>
               <p>THis is an old one, but a good one, and therefore not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amiſte to bee here inſerted; which though it bee knowne to ſome, is queſtionleſſe not to all. A Gentleman of the Vniuerſitie, being great acquaintance with a Doctor, inſomuch that they were very intimate, and indeared friends. It hapned that the Gentleman tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled for the ſpace of ſeuen yeares: In which interim this Doctor was made an Archbiſhop. The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at his returne being glad to heare of his friends preferment, tooke time to viſit him, and came iuſt when they were preparing for dinner. The Archbiſhop more ſtrange in his ſalutation then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; after ſhort greeting askt him where he purpoſed to dine? Hee anſwered, My Lord, where my horſe ſtands, which is both an
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:21212:70"/> Inne, and an Ordinary. Well ſaith my Lord, it may bee before dinner be done you ſhall heare from mee, and ſo parted, without any further complements. The gentleman went to his Inne, and ſate downe among the reſt of the ſtrangers. The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop remembring his promiſe, cals one of his gentlemen, and ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Mullet (which is a Sea fiſh) on the Table; Take this diſh ſaith he, and inquire for ſuch a Gentleman at his Inne, and tell him I haue ſent him this, as a Token of my loue, to mend his Ordinary. The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did. And finding him ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other ſtrangers, told him that his Grace had ſent him that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his loue, to mend his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, he kindly ſeemed to accept it, and humbly thanked his Grace, and the Gentleman that brought it: who being about to take his leaue, the Gentleman cald him back, and deſired to heare of him, whether his Lordſhip had not withall ſent
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:21212:70"/> him either bread to his fiſh, or Beare, or Wine? Who anſwered him, not any of thoſe. Then I pray you ſaith he, remember my ſeruice to your Lord, in a ſheete ſuddenly; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for Pen, Inke, and Paper, writ this diſticke,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Mittitur in diſco</l>
                  <l>Mihipiſcis ab Archiepiſco.</l>
                  <l>Po non ponetur,</l>
                  <l>Quia potus non mihi detur.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The meſſenger bearing the Note to his Lord, he called him backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, told him it might bee his Grace that could forget his friends, might perhaps not well remember his Latine, therefore intreated that he would ſtay to take the ſame lines interpreted into Engliſh, which were thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>There was a fiſh, ſent me in a diſh, by an Archbiſ</l>
                  <l>Hop ſhall not be there, becauſe hee ſent me no Beere.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:21212:71"/>
               <head>118 Truſting for a reckoning.</head>
               <p>ONe came into a Tauerne, Drawer ſaith he, wilt thou truſt me for a Pottle of Wine till the next time I come? Sir ſaith he, I muſt anſwere you in the ſame words, I will truſt you for a Pettle of Wine, till I come againe: ſo brought it, and made him pay for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>119. Strange beaſts to be ſeene.</head>
               <p>TWo pleaſant fellowes comming by a <hi>Bartholmew</hi> Fayer, where amongſt other ſhewes, diuers beaſts were to be ſeene: as a <hi>Leopard,</hi> a <hi>Cat a Mountaine,</hi> and the like: either hauing no money at all, or that little they had being vnwilling to ſpend; one asked the other how they might ſee theſe ſights, and coſt them nothing? The other anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, follow mee, doe as I doe, ſay
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:21212:71"/> nothing and feare nothing. So comming to him that kept the doore, by your leaue Sir ſaith the firſt, and the other ruſhed in after him: ſo taking view of that was to bee ſeene; ſaith one of them, where are theſe monſters which your painted cloth ſpeakes of? here ſaith the Keeper. Where ſaith the other? why here ſaith hee. They hauing ſeene what they came for, a good ieſt (ſaith the firſt) indeed, come a way, doe not vſe thus to make fooles of Gentlemen, and ſo went out of the Roome. Saith the Keeper looking after them, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue theſe two be of that kinde of people that can ſee, and will not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>120. A Emperour of Rome.</head>
               <p>A Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> paſſing by the high way in great pompe, with his Nobility, and Gentry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, two beggers ſitting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaith one of them, Oh how
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:21212:72"/> happy were that man (ſaith the one of them) whom the Emperour would bee pleaſed to make rich. Nay, anſwered the other, happy were that man whom God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would bee pleaſed to make rich. This <hi>Caeſar</hi> ouer-hearing, gaue charge to a Gentleman that was next him, that theſe two Beggars ſhould attend him the next monow at Court. At theſe ſummons the poore men were in a moſt pittifull caſe, fearing they had ſpoke ſome treaſon to bring their liues in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: but the next day appearing in Court, they were by the Emperours appointment brought into the great Chamber, where a Table being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, two rich chaires were placed, and the two beggars in them, and before them two Pyes, made in all reſpects alike, the one full of Gold, the other hauing a baked Feaſant, or ſome other fowle to ſerue for one meale: then were they bid to caſt lots: the Pye with the Feaſant fell
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:21212:72"/> fell to him that ſaid, Oh how happy was he whom the Emperour would pleaſe to make rich, and the Pye of Gold to the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>121. A Scotch Witch.</head>
               <p>A Witch in <hi>Scotland,</hi> arraigned, conuicted, and condemned to bee burnt, being brought to the place of execution, and tyed to the Stake, and the Executioner ready to giue her fire, ſhe caſting her eye on the one ſide ſpide her owne, and onely ſonne, a chubbed young fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and like the child to ſuch a mother: Shee cals to him, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry earneſtly with ſome acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſires him to bring her any quantity of water, or any other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, were it neuer ſo ſmall, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her before her death, for ſhee was extreamely a thirſt. At which he onely ſhooke his head. Shee ſtill the more earneſtly importunes him, ſaying, Why deare child, helpe mee
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:21212:73"/> to ſome drink, be it neuer ſo little, ſo it be any, I care not what it bee, for I am fearfull drie. To whom the young man anſwered, by no means deare Mother will I doe you that iniury, for the drier you are, the better you will burne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>122. A braggard.</head>
               <p>A Terrible braggard boaſted how it was his chance to meet with two of his arch enemies at once, the one ſaith he, I toſt ſo high in the ayre, that had he had at his backe a Bakers basket full of bread, though he had eaten all the way, he would haue beene ſtarued in his fall, ere he would haue reacht the ground: and the other hee ſtrooke ſo deepe into the earth, that he left him no more to bee ſeene aboue ground, but his head and one of his Armes, and theſe to no other end, then to put off his Hat to him, as he had occaſion to paſſe that way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:21212:73"/>
               <head>123. The reuerſion of an houſe.</head>
               <p>ONe came bragging from the Court of Aldermen, ouerioyed with the obtaining of a ſuite, for ſaith he, they haue promiſed mee the leaſe of the next houſe that fals. To whom one ſtanding by replyed, but had it beene my caſe I ſhould haue petitioned for a houſe that ſtood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>A Mayor in the North</head>
               <p>A Mayor of a corporation in the North, iuſt vpon the death of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to an occaſion to aſſemble his Brethren, and to make an Oration, what a good Queene they had loſt: but wiſhed them to take comfort, for <hi>Pompey,</hi> was dead, and <hi>Alexander</hi> was dead, and all the nine worldlings were dead, but none of all theſe was ſo good a Queene as ſhee. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:21212:74"/> ſaith he, in this—as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Schoole-maſter calls it, where there are no Iuſtices of peace, and that no Officers haue any power, but Maiors, Coroners, and Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, by reaſon of which many Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baleroes take their opportunity to commit diuers outrages, and muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, hoping to ſcape vnpuniſhed, but ſaith he, if all other Magiſtrates will take that ſtrict order, that I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to doe, there ſhall none of them all haue the leaſt hope of a reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>125. A man lying ſicke.</head>
               <p>A Man lying very ſicke, hauing his wife dead not long before, one came to him and counſelled him to leaue off the cares of this world, and to thinke of a better place, whither ſaith hee doe you thinke my wife is gone? no doubt ſaid the other by the grace of God but ſhe is in heauen, O ſaith he then
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:21212:74"/> I care not whither I goe, ſo I come not where ſhee is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>126. Of one Fowle a Gentleman.</head>
               <p>ONe <hi>Fowle</hi> by name came vnto a great man in this Kingdome, with a petition, and hauing beene a long ſutor was ſo importunate, that he ſtirred his patience ſo farre, that in a great rage he bad him get him gone for a Woodcocke as hee was: at which the petitioner ſmiling, humbly thankes his Lordſhip, for doing him that preſent curteſie, the Lord turned backe, and thinking he had mockt, askt him what curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie? to which he anſwered his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, truly my Lord, I haue knowne my ſelfe for a Fowle theſe fifty yeres, and vpwards, but never knew what fowle, till now that your Lordſhippe reſolued me: his anſwer pleaſed the Lord, and his ſuit was diſpatcht in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:21212:75"/>
               <head>127. A Gentleman in an Ordinary.</head>
               <p>A Yong Gentleman late come out of the Countrey, and not being well acquainted with <hi>London,</hi> being at an Ordinary, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Gallants, to whom he was a meere ſtranger, Gentlemen ſaith he, I muſt intreat you to take notice of an humour that I haue; the truth is, if any man offer to touch the bread that I cut, and lay by my tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, I preſently ſtabb: ſome ſmiled, others lookt a little ſtrangely vpon the buſineſſe, till at length one Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that ſate next him, beganne thus; I intreat you all likewiſe to take notice of another humour which I haue; and it is this, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt when I perceiue any man begin to ſtab, I ſtab againe, and looking him in the face, ſnacht his bread, and eate it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:21212:75"/>
               <head>128. A Welchman and a Cutpurſe.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman that had a Welch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man waiting on him came to ſee a Play, and drawing his purſe at the doore which was well furniſht with Crownes, was watcht by a Cutpurſe, who dogd him, and tooke his ſeat cloſe by him, the Welch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſitting behind his Maſter, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued that whilſt hee was ſeriouſly minding the ſport, the Cheater had cunningly conuayed his purſe out of his pocket, and was about to riſe, when preſently the Welſhman without more words drawes out his knife, and with one ſlaſh cut off the Cheaters eare, who ſtartling at the ſuddenneſſe of the act, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the ſmart, lookt behinde him, and askt him what hee meant by it? The Welchman hauing his eare in his hand anſwered no harme done good friend, no harme done, giue hur Maſter hur purſe, and I will giue hur, hur care.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:21212:76"/>
               <head>129. A Gentleman and a Parſon.</head>
               <p>A Pleaſant conceited Gentleman riding by the high way, in the companie of ſome friends, ſpyed a Parſon of the Country before him, ſaid, Gentlemen yonder is a Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, let vs mend our pace, and you ſhall heare me poſe him with a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and after a ſleight ſalutation, Maſter Parſon ſaith hee, I pray you can you reſolue mee what part of ſpeech is <hi>Qui mihi diſcipulus,</hi> yes Sir, I can, ſaith the parſon, <hi>puer es cupis at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deceri,</hi> the words are ſo familiar that I hope they need no Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>130. Of Graue Maurice, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe Spinola.</head>
               <p>IT is reported that when Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> came firſt with an Army into the Low-Countryes, that he ſent word to Graue <hi>Maurice</hi> hee
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:21212:76"/> was now come ſomewhat neerer him, and purpoſed to ſit as cloſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him as his Caſſocke to his backe; to whom hee returned this anſwer, that hee had often knowne when a ſouldier hath tooke a Merchants Cloake from his ſhoulders, but that a Merchant ſhould plucke off a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Caſſock, he had ſeldome heard or neuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>131. Of Biſhop <hi>Gardiner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Haue read that Biſhop <hi>Gardiner</hi> being depoſed in King <hi>Edwards</hi> dayes, and ſent to the Tower, a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low meeting him in the way, in great deriſion ſaluted him with a low Congee, and bade him good morrow Biſhop <hi>Olim,</hi> whoſe ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hee returned in theſe few words, <hi>Gramercy knaue ſemper.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:21212:77"/>
               <head>132. An vnhappy Vintners Boy.</head>
               <p>TWo Diuines walking along the Towne, the end of the Lane which they ſhould paſſe through was choaked with Carts, and the corner thereof being a Tauerne, and hauing one doore into the Lane, and another into the ſtreet, they made vſe of the preſent, and as they paſt through, the boy at the barre ſeeing they called for no wine, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen ſaith he, is it your cuſtome to goe thorow a Church, and not to ſay your prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>133. Playing with words.</head>
               <p>A Diuine willing to play more with words, then to be ſerious in the expounding of his text, ſpake thus in ſome part of his ſermon; this Dyall ſhewes wee muſt dye all, yet notwithſtanding, all houſes are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Ale-houſes: our cares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:21212:77"/> into cures: our Paradice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a paire of Dice: our mariage to a merry age: our Matrimony to a matter of money: our Diuines into dry Vines: It was not ſo in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> Ah no, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>134. Of a Landlord and his Tenant.</head>
               <p>A Tenant had a horſe, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times lookt into his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords grounds, for no hedge nor ditch could ſtop him, but he would ſtill feed where hee ſaw the beſt graſſe, at length the Landlord ſent word vnto his Tenant, that peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily if euer hee tooke his horſe in his ground againe, he would cut off his taile. This word being brought vnto the Tenant, hee gaue the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger this ſhort anſwer; My Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord ſaith he, may doe his pleaſure, but tell him againe from me, if he cut off his tayle, Ile cut off his eares. The Landlord vpon this menace ſueth him, and binds him to the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:21212:78"/> peace and good behauiour, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe came to bee decided, the Tenant pleaded that his Landlord had much miſtaken him, for his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer reached no further then thus: That if his Landlord did cut off his horſes tayle, he purpoſed to cut off his horſes eares, and to make him crop-ear'd, as the other had made him cur-taild.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>135. Of an old Beggar.</head>
               <p>AN old Beggar in <hi>Cornwall</hi> liued till hee was aboue ſeuen ſcore yeares, whoſe name was <hi>Ball:</hi> And being asked by many, what courſe he tooke to continue his life to that length of yeares: Hee would ſtill make anſwer, he loued a cup of good Ale, and that he vſed to drinke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, but of other Phyſicke hee neuer taſted any. The Beggar dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a witty gentleman of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try made of him this Epitaph:</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:21212:78"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Heere <hi>Ball</hi> the <hi>quondam</hi> Beggar lyes,</l>
                  <l>who counted by his Tale,</l>
                  <l>Some ſeven ſcore Winters and above,</l>
                  <l>ſuch vertue is in Ale.</l>
                  <l>Ale was his meat, ale was his drinke</l>
                  <l>Ale did his life deceiue,</l>
                  <l>Ver could he ſtill haue drunke his ale,</l>
                  <l>he yet had beene aliue.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>136. A rich man and a Scholler.</head>
               <p>A Rich Citizen, whoſe houſe was often frequented by Schollers, demanded of one of them what was the reaſon why Aldermens and great Merchants threeſholds were ſo often trod vpon by ſchollers; and on the contrary part, why ſchollers Chambers were ſo ſeldome fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented by wealthy Citizens. He made him this anſwer: Becauſe ſchollers know what they want, but rich men doe not. Another being asked how the learned differ from the vnlearned, replyed, In
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:21212:79"/> the ſame ſort that horſes which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver felt the curbe or bridle differ from thoſe that haue beene carefully brought vp and mannaged. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demanded whether a beggar or a man illiterate or vnlearned wanted moſt; It was anſwered, An ignorant man, becauſe a beggar on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wanteth money, but the other lacketh all things to a man belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>137. A Lawyer and a Diuine.</head>
               <p>A Graue Diuine hauing a ſute in Law, feed his Counſellour, who pleaded very eloquently in his behalfe, and caried the cauſe cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the aduerſary: The Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man comming after to giue him thankes: The Lawyer ſomewhat proud of his ſucceſſe, ſpake to him in this manner: Now Sir, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit had you reaped by your Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if my Rhetoricke had not helped you out of the Bryars, to whom he
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:21212:79"/> replyed and ſaid, This profit I haue gotten by it, that I haue brought before you an honeſt cauſe; And all the evidences alledged in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, are moſt iuſt and true.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>138. Of Swimming.</head>
               <p>AMongſt other communication at the Table, there was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe held concerning ſwimming, in which many excellent in that art were remembred: One of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany liſtning to their talke, Well my Maſters ſaith he, you talke of ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, but for mine owne part I can ſwimme no more then a Gooſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>139. Of a ſhe-ſeruant that came to take her oath.</head>
               <p>A Waiting Gentlewoman being ſummoned into a Court to take an Oath (for ſhe was ſerued in with a <hi>ſub paena</hi>) The Examiner asked how hee ſhould write her
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:21212:80"/> downe: A Mayde, a Wife, or a Widow? ſhee told him that hee ſhould write her downe a Mayd, for ſhee neuer had had any huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. Hee finding her a prettie handſome ſmugge wench, asked her how old ſhe was; ſhee told him about the age of ſix and twentie: ſix and twentie (ſaith he willing to ſport with her:) then take heed ſaith he, what you ſweare, for you are now vpon your oath, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, may I ſecurely ſet you downe Mayd, being of thoſe yeares? The wench made a pauſe, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a while with her ſelfe: I pray you Sir ſaith ſhee, ſtay your hand a little, and write mee downe young woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:21212:80"/>
               <head>140. Another Gentleman and a Parſon.</head>
               <p>A Countrey man ouer-taking a Parſon, ſaluteth him with a how now blacke Coate? Why blacke coate ſaith the Parſon? I vſe to call all parſons ſo ſaith the other O Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Saunders,</hi> how doe you ſir, ſaith the Parſon? Why <hi>Saunders,</hi> ſaith the other? I vſe to call all Iacks ſo, ſaith the Parſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>141. A Lawyer at the Barre.</head>
               <p>A Lawyer pleading earneſtly in behalfe of his client at the Bar, this caſe ſaith he is plaine, and hath beene warranted already by two great, and ſufficient Lawyers; the one of them is (as wee make no doubt) in heauen, the other (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one that was then made a Iudge) is at this time in an higher place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:21212:81"/>
               <head>142. The Tenant to an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop.</head>
               <p>A Simple man that was Tenant to an Archbiſhop, came to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, to tender his rent, and by the Porter was directed to the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard: to whom hee came, and told him that he had brought his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips worſhip ſome money for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Cottage in which hee then dwelt. The Steward receiued it, but withall told him, that he muſt leaue out Worſhip, &amp; put in Grace. But before the ſmall ſumme was told, the Archbiſhop came through the great Hall, and demanded of the Steward what the Poore mans bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe was? The Tenant preuented his anſwere, made two or three low legs, and began againe with, if it pleaſe his Worſhip: but the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard prompting him, told him hee muſt ſay Grace. Muſt I, ſaid the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:21212:81"/> why then I will, and holding vp his hands began, <hi>The eyes of all things, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>133. Of a ſigne.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman paſſing through a faire Towne, and ſpying at an Inne gate the ſigne of a blew Bore, but miſerably, and moſt vnskilfully drawne; rides into the middle of the yard, and cals aloud for ſome one to take money, downe comes the Chamberlaine, and asked his Worſhip what hee had had? Had (ſaith he) nothing: but ſtill importuned him to take money, for he is deſirous to take view of the Monſter to be ſeene. The fellow asked him what Monſter? Marry, that ſtrange Monſter ſaith he, whoſe picture you haue hung out to bee ſeene. Why ſir ſaith he, you miſtake your ſelfe, that is our Signe. Your Signe ſaith the Gentleman? then I prethee let it hang there ſtill for a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:21212:82"/> ſigne that the Painter was an aſſe, and thy Maſter a Coxcombe who bought it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>144. Of a Tranſlator.</head>
               <p>ONe that had tranſlated many books and Volumes, at length publiſhing the hiſtory of <hi>Suetonius Tranquillus</hi> in Engliſh, a pleaſant Gentleman writ this diſtick:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Philemon <hi>with Tranſlations doth ſo fill vs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He will not let</hi> Suetonius <hi>bee</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillus.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>145. A Marriner in a ſtorme.</head>
               <p>A Young Marriner being in a great ſtorme at Sea, and in the night when euery one had left their labours, and were at prayers, this fellow had nothing in his mouth, but oh that I could ſee but two Starres, or but one of the two: and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:21212:82"/> of theſe words he made ſo often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition, that diſturbing the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the reſt; at length one askt him what two Starres, or what one he meant? To whom hee replyed, Oh that I could but ſee the Starre in Cheapſide, or the Starre in Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſtreete I care not whether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>146. A deſperate Saylor.</head>
               <p>ANother deſperate Saylor being in a ſhip that was accidently ſet on fire, &amp; burning vnder them, when there was no hope of the life of any man of them, but to periſh betwixt the two Elements of fire, and water, hee ſtanding vpon the hatches, and is it ſo, ſaith hee? Nay then ſome roaſted, and ſome ſod, and ſo deſperately leapt into the ſea.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:21212:83"/>
               <head>147. A ſhort Cloake.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman ſpying one walke in a muſt pittifull ſhort Cloake, ſaith to a friend that was then walking with him, Did you euer ſee a poore man weare his Cloake ſo ſhort? Oh there is helpe for that replyed the other, for I ſee by his countenance that hee can finde a way to weare it longer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>148. Of Wine.</head>
               <p>ONe preſented a Drunkard for his Newyeares gift, with theſe few lines:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Whil'ſt in my Pot or Glaſſe I keepe my Wine,</l>
                  <l>I boldly dare preſume that they are mine:</l>
                  <l>But when the Pot I by the Glaſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure,</l>
                  <l>Being drunke, the Maſter in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants power.</l>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:21212:83"/>
                  <l>I haue not it, it hath mee, all I haue</l>
                  <l>Is to bee made a priſoner to my ſlaue.</l>
                  <l>What was my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſſaile, now I Idol call,</l>
                  <l>For I before it muſt both kneele and fall.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>149. A Welchman arraigned.</head>
               <p>A Welchman arraigned, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted, by the fauour of the Bench, hauing his booke granted him, when hee was burnt in the hand, they bid him ſay God ſaue the King. Nay ſaith he, God bleſſe my father and my mother, for had not they brought mee vp to write and reade, I might haue beene han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for all the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:21212:84"/>
               <head>150. Of Card-playing.</head>
               <p>A Parſon in the Countrey liuing amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his Pariſhoners &amp; neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors wel, would ſometimes at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired hours for his recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, play at Cards amongſt them, for which he was much enuied of a Puritane Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the Officiall of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Theſe meeting on a market day amongſt the chiefe men of the Countrey where the Parſon was there preſent, his two aduerſaries began in the Ordinary openly to reproue him at the Table for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Card-playing, not ſitting his Calling. Who hearing them with ſome impatience, and the reſt atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding how he could acquit himſelfe, he thus began: Right Worſhipfull, and the reſt of my friend, I am here charged by Maſter Iuſtice, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Officiall to be a common Card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>player: to which I anſwere, If all men would make that vſe of it that
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:21212:84"/> I doe, it would ſeeme as pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as I ſhal make it appeare excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in me: for mine own part, I neuer ſee an Ace, but I apprehend that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which ought to bee betwixt man and wife. If a Duce, the loue which ſhould bee betwixt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. If a Tra, if two of my Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners bee at ods, how needfull a thing it is for a third perſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them, and make them friend; and ſo of the reſt. Nor doe I looke vpon a king, but preſently I apprehend the alleageance due to my Prince, and Soueraigne. Nor on a queene, but I remember her ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Maieſty, and the reuerence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to her eſtate. Nor doe I caſt mine eye vpon a Knaue, but he puts me in minde either of you Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iuſtice, or you Maſter Officiall, or of ſome other of my good friends. The Iuſtice and Officiall were anſwered; and the plaine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Parſon for his ieſt ſake, both applauded and excuſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:21212:85"/>
               <head>151. An Epitaph made vpon an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Cobler.</head>
               <q>
                  <l>HEere lyes a Cobler that dwelt in the Strand,</l>
                  <l>Who though he was ſtill on the mending hand:</l>
                  <l>Yet by the force of wind and weather,</l>
                  <l>His ſole was rent from his vpper lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>152. Of a Gentleman viſiting of his friend.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman comming to giue his ſicke friend a courteous vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, found him extremly faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted and wondrous timerous of death, inſomuch that he grew much aſhamed at his too much puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, eſpecially in regard of the ſtanders by: for hee had nothing in his mouth but ah, woe is mee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> no friend neere which will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> rid me from this paine
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:21212:85"/> and anguiſh which I now ſuffer? Theſe words were iterated ſo often that the Gentleman drawing his ſword with a menacing looke ſaid, yes ſir, you haue one friend yet left that for your ſake will doe it, and withall aymed the point directly againſt his breſt. At which proffer the ſicke Gentlemen raiſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe out of his bed, intreated him to ſtay his hand, for his deſire was to be rid out of his paine, but not out of his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>153. Of a Captaine that was to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted.</head>
               <p>ONe Captaine <hi>Leonard Sampſon</hi> well known about this towne, being indebted was way-layed by his Creditour, who had feed Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants to arreſt him. Theſe ſpying him in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> were ſtealing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him thinking to clap him on the ſhoulders vnawares, which a Gentleman a friend of his eſpying,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:21212:86"/> cryed out alowd vnto him and ſaid, <hi>The Philiſtins bee vpon thee Sampſon,</hi> at which words hee ſuddenly look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ign backe, and eſpying the Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poles, drew his ſword, and by that meanes eſcaped from the Arreſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>154. Of two knaves accuſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</head>
               <p>TWo fellowes of notorious and bad liues, came to complaine at a publike Aſſizes one of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ript vp ſo many cheats, vile pranks and miſchieuous diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that both ſeemed exceeding bad, and hardly it was to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed which was worſe, vpon whom the Iudge gaue ſentence, that the one ſhould inſtantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Realme, and that the other ſhould as ſuddenly follow him, and ſee his ſentence to bee ſtrictly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:21212:86"/>
               <head>155. Of a Vintners boy.</head>
               <p>TWo Divines paſſing through a Tauerne and calling for no wine, the Vintners boy ſeeing them, what ſaith he, two Preachers goe through the Church and not offer to ſay their prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>156. Of Auguſtus Caeſar.</head>
               <p>IT is reported of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> demanded a reward of him alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by reaſon of his vertue and deſert it was noiſed in the City hee had receiued great gifts of him already: but hee knowing him to be a man of words, without merit, returned him onely this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Well friend ſaith hee, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the city reports, I would wiſh thee not to beleeue it. A ſecond, who had bin a Captain of the Horſe, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:21212:87"/> being caſheired from his Command petitioned vnto the Emperour, that in regard he had left his place, yet it would pleaſe him to allow him an annuall penſion: which he did not deſire for any profit or gaine, but ſaith he, to ſalue my reputation, that the world may not report that I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited my place by any inſufficiency or negligence: but rather out of my freewill made thereof a voluntary reſignation. To whom the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour made this anſwer: well honeſt ſouldier, doe not then ſpare to make report to thee a yearly penſion, and if any one ſhall chance hereafter to queſtion me about it, I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that thou haſt one. A third (being a yong Nobleman and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Herennius</hi>) hauing through his miſgouernment and diſorder beene commanded to avoid the Campe, he earneſtly beſought the Emperor that hee would not doe vnto him publike diſgrace. For Sir (ſaith he)
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:21212:87"/> if I be turned off with ſuch diſgraces I ſhall neuer dare to ſhew my face; either vnto my Father, or any of my Noble kinſmen in <hi>Rome:</hi> For what ſhall I ſay vnto them? why ſaith <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> ſay vnto them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this: that thou and I were at ſome difference, and in the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof, I loſt thy countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and fauour. A fourth in a skirmiſh being ſtrucke with a ſtone and wounded in the face, ſo that he was much disfigured, yet becauſe hee bore that viſible marke in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, he thereupon grew inſolent, boaſting of what great acts of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrie hee had performed in the warres; which hee not ſparing to doe in the ſight of the Emperor, He thus derided his arrogance in theſe few words: Well Sir, (ſaith hee) Take heed how you looke backe againe the next time that you finde an opportunity to runne away from the battell. Another time, a Knight of <hi>Rome</hi> deceaſing, who had the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:21212:88"/> opinion to be a rich man, when the Executors came to examine his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, it was found that he dyed, to the value of two hundred Crownes worſe then nothing: and yet all his life time caried himſelfe brauely and nobly: when this was reported to the Emperour, he ſent to buy his quilt and mattrice, which vſed to lye vpon his bed (for all his goods were ſold at an out-cry) one of his Noblemen demanding the reaſon thereof, He anſwered, onely for this cauſe, to ſleepe quietly in the night. For no queſtion there was ſome great vertue in theſe coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, otherwiſe he could neuer haue reſted to ſecurely being indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo much money. This was that <hi>Auguſtus</hi> who ſaid, I found <hi>Rome</hi> made of Beech, but I hope to leaue it built of Marble, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:21212:88"/>
               <head>157. Of Diogenes.</head>
               <p>DIogenes being taken Priſoner was brought into the Market place to bee ſold for a ſlaue, who ſtill as the Cryer made proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who will by a ſlaue. He ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded him with a loud clamour, and asked what was hee that would buy a Maſter. A rich Cheffe made vp onely out of money bagges had built a wondrous beautifull houſe, with this Inſcription vpon the great Gate (which was the common en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance) <hi>Let no evill thing enter here. Diogenes</hi> comming by and reading what was there inſcribed, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the man withall that built it, made inquiry of the neighbours, which wayes the man went into his houſe. A man of euill condition, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him whether he thought there were any gods or no? he anſwered,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:21212:89"/> I muſt needs beleeue there are gods, becauſe I confidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that thou art hated of them. Of a Prodigall whoſe eſtate he knew could not laſt long, hee begged an an Almes, and asked no leſſe then according to account comes to fiue pounds: The yong Heire deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him what his reaſon was to craue ſo great a ſumme of money from him, when others had deſired at once but an halfe peny: The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is (anſwered he) becauſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that ſpend ſparingly, I am in hope to receiue againe, but of thee that art an vnthrift, I am afraid I ſhal neuer beg hereafter. To a fellow that had before beene foyled in wraſtling and other exerciſes, and finding him now to practiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke; He thus ſaid, my friend, I doe much commend thy policy, for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſafe courſe, to deſtroy theſe by Phyſicke, who haue diſgraced thee by wraſtling. To one that asked him what hee would haue to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:21212:89"/> take a ſound blow on the pate; hee anſwered, an Iron Head Peece. To a wanton woman fitting in a ſtately Horſlitter, hee ſaid, truely another Cage would better become that load. And to another who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in what ſtate it were beſt to marry a wife, hee anſwered, that for a young man it was too ſoone, and for an old man too late, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>145. Of a Country fellow and a Peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree.</head>
               <p>A Country-fellow at <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi> Faire, comming through the <hi>Charterhouſe</hi> in the Euening, chanced to finde a mellow peere, which ſome had ſcattered out of their pocket, and taſting it, looked vp vnto the great Elmes grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, imagining it had fallen from thence. So well hee liked the taſt of it, that hee layd by his
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:21212:90"/> Cloake, and with a Crabtree Cudgell which hee had then about him, he did ſo belabour the trees, that thoſe which paſſed by wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what hee meant, and asking him the reaſon, he told them, hee purpoſed onely to fill his belly from theſe Peere trees, for hee did not thinke there were the like in all his Countrey: They ſuffered him with ſome laughing till he had ſufficiently tyred himſelfe, and then bid him get (like a foole as he was) to his owne lodging.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:21212:90"/>
               <head>259. Stratford vpon Auon.</head>
               <p>ONe trauelling through <hi>Stratford</hi> vpon <hi>Auon,</hi> a Towne moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable for the birth of famous <hi>William Shakeſpeare,</hi> and walking in the Church to doe his deuotion, eſpyed a thing there worthy obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, which was a tombeſtone laid more then three hundred years agoe, on which was ingrauen an Epitaph to this purpoſe, I <hi>Thomas</hi> ſuch a one, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> my wife here vnder lye buried, and know Reader <hi>I. R. C.</hi> and <hi>I. Chryſtoph. Q.</hi> are aliue at this houre to witneſſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>160. An old Gooſe.</head>
               <p>HENRY the fourth King of <hi>France</hi> of late famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, being vpon a long march where victuals at that time were very ſcarce, &amp; he extreamely a hungred, at length an honeſt Gentleman
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:21212:91"/> brought a legge of a Brood gooſe carbonadoed: at which the King long tugging, and not able to pull it aſunder. <hi>Mort die</hi> (ſaith hee) this is ſure a limbe of that Gooſe, that in <hi>Cumellus</hi> his time by her gabling ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Romane Capitoll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>161. An honourable Theefe.</head>
               <p>AN Earle in times paſt in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, hauing made ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous voyages abroad, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with great prizes from the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyard: meeting with another yong Earle, who by his fathers death was newly come both to his Meanes, and Title: after ſome Noble gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, they fell in diſcourſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Sea fights, and ſhips taken from the Enemy. At lengh, I wonder ſaith the ſouldier Earle, that your Lordſhip being of ſuch remarke in the Court, and Kingdome, doth not for your greater honour vndertake in your owne perſon ſome Noble
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:21212:91"/> enterpriſe at ſea againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy the Spanyard, as I, and others haue done. To whom hee gaue this modeſt anſwere; My wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lord, I thanke God, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſo carefull, that hee hath husbanded ſo my preſent Meanes, and fortunes, that I am able to liue of mine owne reuenues at home, without any need to goe theeuing abroad. Why my Lord ſaith he, doe you hold me to be a Theefe? Oh yes, (with pardon my Lord) an honourable Theefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>162. Of S P. Q. R.</head>
               <p>A Ieſt touching theſe letters, <hi>S. P. Q. R. Senatus, Populuſque Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> It ſo hapned that a new Pope being elected meerly for his deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and auſterity of life; as vſing an extraordinary ſpare diet, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeldome ſeene ſo much as to ſmile: Yet after his Inauguration comming to ſit in <hi>Pontificalibus,</hi> hee vſed to
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:21212:92"/> feed high, to laugh heartily, and to countenance Ieſters, and Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foones to make him merry at his Table, which being obſerued, one ſets vp theſe foure words, being correſpondent to the foure former letters: <hi>Sancte Pater quare rides?</hi> Holy Father, why doe you laugh? To which the next day was vnder writen, <hi>Rideo quia Papa ſum,</hi> I laugh becauſe I am <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>163. An Oppreſſour.</head>
               <p>ONe told a great oppreſſour he might kill beggars by the law. The other asked him the reaſon? He anſwered, becauſe he was before hand in their number, for hee could not kill ſo many as hee had made before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>144. A writ Noſe.</head>
               <p>THere was a man whoſe Noſe leaned more towards one ſide
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:21212:92"/> then the other. One diſpoſed to play the wag with him, ſir ſaith he, I know what your noſe is not made of, and I know what it is made of, Firſt, I will aſſure you it is not made of wheat. What then ſaith the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? I will be iudge by all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany if it be not made of Rie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>165. Of vſury.</head>
               <p>ONe bitterly railing againſt vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and extortion, made the ſin equall with wilfull murther: but after vpon ſome vrgent neceſſity, comming to borrow money of one of his pariſhioners, deſired to haue it for three moneths <hi>gratis.</hi> Who anſwered him, truely ſir, if to lend money vpon vſe be in your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion as great a ſinne as murther, to lend money <hi>gratis,</hi> in my conceit can be a ſinne no leſſe then man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:21212:93"/>
               <head>166. A Scholler and a Townſman.</head>
               <p>ONe meaſuring a Scholler and a Townſman, the queſtion was, which was the higſteſt? The party hauing at that time in his hand a Pitchforke, thus anſwered; When I had firſt ſet them backe to back, and after well conſidered them Brow to Brow, I found the Townſman to bee higher then the Scholler by thus much pointing to the tines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>167. Of an ignorant fellow.</head>
               <p>ONe of the great ſtone letters fel from the top of Northampton houſe, and beat out a ſchollers braines. It hapned not long after that an honeſt good fellow that could neither write nor reade, (for ſuch was the vnhappineſſe of his bringing vp) being in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of three or foure very ingenious
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:21212:93"/> Gentlemen, vpon the ſudden breaks out into a deepe melancholly, and ſaith, Well, I thanke God, I can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther write nor reade. One of the reſt ſmiling, replies, you ſpeake ſtrangely, for I thanke God, and ſo may the reſt that are here, that wee can doe both. All's one for that ſaith hee, yet let my ſelfe, and many Captaines, and other braue fellowes about the Towne (naming a great many) bee ſtill thankfull that wee can doe neither. They asked his reaſon? He gave them this ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, becauſe ſaith hee, wee can walke the ſtreetes with that ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that you booke men cannot. They deſired him to expreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſaith hee, if one letter falling from the top of a great houſe had the power to knock out the braines of a ſcholler, what ſafety ſhould we liue in, to be troubled with foure and twenty letters? Now thanked be heauen, ſaith he, for as we haue nothing to doe with letters, ſo I ſee
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:21212:94"/> no reaſon why letters can haue any thing to doe with vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>168. Anola horſe.</head>
               <p>A Horſe being iudged to be paſt his beſt dayes, one ſeeing what he was likely to come to, replyed, that then hee was neere his dog dayes. It being further demanded how old he was? The anſwere was made, that for this yeares he might very lawfully ſet his foote vnto a bond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>169. Fire and Toe.</head>
               <p>ONe ſeeing a fellow warming his feet by a hot ſeacole fire; my friend ſaith hee, what doe you meane to put fire and Toe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:21212:94"/>
               <head>170. Borrowing of a Cloake.</head>
               <p>A Poore decayed Gentleman, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pound or ſold his Cloake; came to another, to whom hee was knowne, and deſired, (knowing he was well furniſht) to ſupply him with one, for two or three dayes whilſt his owne came from dreſſing, and then hee would vndoubtedly returne it: the Gentleman anſwered him againe: that hee had not any ſpare Cloake, but ſuch as belonged to one ſuite or another and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite his cloathes hee was loath: yet vpon his importunity, hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, to lend him a thinne ſtuffe Cloake, that belonged to a Summer ſuit, and that vpon promiſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two or three dayes, to reſtore it: but dayes, weekes, and months came, in which time hee neuer heard of the Gentleman, but ſome halfe a yeare after, it was his chance to meete him, in the midſt of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:21212:95"/> in a cold miſty morning, with the ſame cloake vpon him, worne to the very threeds, and ſcarce able to hang vpon him; which the other ſeeing, ſtayeth him, and challengeth him, vpon his breach of promiſe, and tells him withall, that in regard of the priuate cheate, hee will doe him a publike diſgrace: &amp; take his owne (howſoeuer worth nothing) whereſoeuer hee findes it, and ſo offers to pluck it from off his ſhoulders. The other deſires him to forbeare, and tells him hee may doe more then he can anſwer. How ſaith hee, haue I not to doe with mine owne, what I pleaſe? In this caſe (anſwers hee) you cannot. Giue me your reaſon, ſaith the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Then thus, ſaith hee, when, I borrowed this cloake of you, I was a Proteſtant, but ſince am turned Roman Catholike, and comming to my confeſſor amongſt others. I told him how vngratefully I had vſed you, concerning this poore
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:21212:95"/> garment, for which hee inioyned mee this penance, Haſt thou ſaid he, had the pleaſure to weare this light Cloake all this warme Sommer? the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I command thee as a puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, not to leaue it off for the ſpace of this cold, and froſty winter, and ſo ſlipt away from him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>171. One begd for a foole.</head>
               <p>A Knight, held to bee a very wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in his life, left behind him a ſonne, and heire that was none of the beſt witted, to inherit his Land: who was begd for a foole, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned into the court of Wards for his anſwer: when queſtion was made vnto him, what hee could ſay for himſelfe, why his lands ſhould not be taken from him, hee ſaid, It is reported, that my father was a wiſeman, and begott a foole to inherit his eſtate after his death, who can tell, him that I a foole, may beget a wiſeman to inherit after me
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:21212:96"/> his anſwer carried it, and he, and his remaine in poſſeſſion of the ſame reuenues vnto this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>172. A Traueller drowned.</head>
               <p>A Traueller reported to be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a friend of his being in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, when the letters came, that brought the firſt newes of his death: fetcht a great ſigh, with theſe words, God reſt his ſoule, for he is gone the way of all fleſh. Nay ſaith another the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtanding by, if hee be drowned hee is rather gone he way of all fiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>173. A Knight of Italy.</head>
               <p>A Knight of <hi>Italy</hi> ſitting downe to a feaſt, and ſeeing two anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent neglected gentlemen ſtanding by, (who had beene great ſouldiers) whileſt the youngmen diſpoſed of themſelues, at the table, hee inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly roſe from the table, and to the reſt of the gueſts ſaid, Moſt iuſtly ought
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:21212:96"/> wee to afford theſe Gentlemen places whereon to ſit, for had they not beene in ſuch a great battle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Turke, we had not at this time, had any thing whereof to eate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>174. A Gentleman boaſting of his wit.</head>
               <p>A Young Gentleman, being at an ordinary was boaſting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly of his trauells, adding withall that he ſpent three yeares abroade in forreigne Countries, and liued without any Exhibition from his parents, and friends; or any ſupply from his Country: But meerly by his owne naturall wit, to whom another anſwered, truly ſir, I thinke neuer any trauelled at a more eaſie rate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>175. A Iuſtice and a Baud.</head>
               <p>A Notorious Baud being brought before a Iuſtice of Peace, for many leud demenours, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:21212:97"/> for keeping a common brothell houſe, was examined of diuerſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, all which ſhe obſtinately denied, though there were proofes ſufficient, apparantly to conuict her, which the Iuſtice hearing, Well, huſwife ſaith he, you keepe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon brothell houſe, &amp; I will maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. Marry I thanke your good worſhip ſaith ſhee, for ſuch a ſupport I haue great need of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>176. Of a Citizen, and a Gardeners Boy.</head>
               <p>A Rich tradeſman in the City, tooke a Summer houſe in the country, with a faire Garden land Orchard, amongſt many other pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, one was commended vnto him, which as yet had neuer borne any fruit, the Citizen gaue the gardiner a great charge, that when the time of the yeare came, hee ſhould bee carefull to ſaue the Apples that came of it, in regard the graft was
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:21212:97"/> commended vnto him by ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a friend, the gardiner did ſo, and ſent them to <hi>London</hi> by a young lad his ſon, who preſented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being 3 in number, to his Maſter &amp; Miſtris, they ſeeing them look ſo louely, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fell to eating them, he one &amp; ſhe another: the boy looking wiſhly vpon them, and ſhee obſeruing it, I pray you husband giue the one Apple to the boy, for he may long: which hee did, the boy preſently drawes his knife to pare his Apple before he eates it, the Gentlewoman noting it; askt him why he did not eate it as they did with the skin on, marry quoth he, if pleaſe you, one of the three ſlipt out of my hand by the way into the dirt, and this may bee it for ought that I know.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:21212:98"/>
               <head>177. An old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar.</head>
               <p>AN old Vicar in Lancaſhire, that read prayers in a Chappell of eaſe, hauing but one ſonne, bred him in the vniuerſity, whoſe name was Iohn, who profited well, proued a graduate: and was made miniſter: who comming home in a vacation to ſee his father, was requeſted by the pariſhioners to beſtow a Sunday Sermon on them, who willingly aſſented, and comming into the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and reading his text, I Iohn ſaw the new Ieruſalem, his father heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, preſently ſtarts vp, and ſaid aloud, beleeue him not my good neighbours, for he is a young lying knaue, he was neuer in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, no further then Cambridge in all his life, but one iogging him on the elbow, ſaid, peace Maſter Vicar for ſhame, will you not giue him leaue to read his text? Oh was it his text ſaith he, nay then let him proceed a Gods name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:21212:98"/>
               <head>178. Two Debawſht fellowes.</head>
               <p>TWo debawſht Fellowes, propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing diuerſe courſes how to liue; ſaith one, my purpoſe is to keepe a Tobacco ſhop: How wilt thou come by Tobacco, and pipes, ſaith the other? why ſaith he, I will goe vpon the ticket. But ſaith hee, how wilt thou doe for a ſhop? Marry ſaith he, I haue iuſt ſo much money, as will ſerue for earneſt; and I will take one by the quarter. How wilt thou doe ſaith his friend, to pay the rent? hee beginning to anſwer, that when the quarter day comes, the other preuenting him, ſaying, then lay the Key vnder the doore, no anſwered hee againe, I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought me of a farre better courſe, I wil according to the old Prouerbe, put my pipes in my bag and ſo get me away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:21212:99"/>
               <head>179. A lame Horſe.</head>
               <p>VPon a Friday in Smithfield one willing to put off a lame Horſe, and therefore not willing to haue him rid; had tied him by the Bridle to the Railes, a chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man liking the Nag came ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neare his price, becauſe the ſeller warranted him ſound of wind and limbe, but before hee would part with his money, deſirous to ſee what metall hee had, hee rid him vpon the Stones, and perceiued the poore Iade to halt downe right, at which the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man vexing, asking the other if hee was not aſhamed, to put a lame vnſeruiceable Iade vpon him, and warrant him ſound. To whom the other anſwered, I aſſure you hee is as ſound, as any Horſe in England, but that it was your
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:21212:99"/> fortune to try him when his foote was a ſleepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>180. A Woman, and her Husband.</head>
               <p>IN the time of auricular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, a woman who not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, was Iealous of her husband, came to the confeſſor to enquire of him, whether at any time hee had reuealed any ſuch thing in his confeſſion: and preuailed ſo farre with him, by vow of concealment, that hee told her, that if within ſome few dayes, after his next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to confeſſion, hee preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her with cloath to make her a new gowne, as in the way of recompence for ſome iniury be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore done her, ſhe might apprehend ſome thing, but more then that ſhee could not get from him. The woman well conceiuing as it was,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:21212:100"/> found as hee had told her, that her good man preſented her with a new gowne, and after many faire, and flattering words, Sweet wife ſaith hee, how doſt thou like the cloath? ſhe conceiuing how the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines went, marry ſo well my moſt deare and louing husband, that I vow ere many dayes goe ouer my head to prouide you a cloake out of the ſame peice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:21212:100"/>
               <head>181. A Towneſman and a Scholler.</head>
               <p>A Towneſman in one of the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities with his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on one ſide of the way, a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Schollers were on the other, both being within hearing at ſuch a time, as a droue of Oxen was to paſſe betwixt them, when one of the Towneſmen according to his wit thought to toſſe a ieſt among them, ſaid, Thoſe that come yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeeme to be ſchollers by their long tailes. To whom the ſchollers replyed, But they appeare to bee Towneſmen by their high fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>182. Of fiue Vintners.</head>
               <p>FIue Vintners riding into <hi>Kent,</hi> to be merry, vpon horſes hyred or borrowed, in their return co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:21212:101"/> through <hi>Greenwich,</hi> they alighted at the Tauerne next to the bridge, and there fell a healthing ſo long, till it grew towards night, one tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling on a bed, another ſate drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in a chaire, onely one ſtood ſtiffely to it, and told them plainly if they would not get vp and take horſe hee would leaue them there, be inſtantly gone, and commend them to their wiues at <hi>London:</hi> but they all agreed to ſtay there that night, to ſet vp their horſes, and to take the benefit of the morning. With this anſwere away goes he. It being now growne darke, and he keeping the Londoners pace a tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuie: it hapned that within a little of <hi>Debtford,</hi> a dead horſe lay full in the way, iuſt of the ſame colour of that on which hee rid. His liue horſe ſtumbles at the dead, both are ouerthrowne, but the foure legs being nimbler then the two, gets vp firſt, and away he plods onward his iourney towards <hi>London.</hi> The
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:21212:101"/> Vintner much bruiſed with the fall riſeth with difficulty, and curſeth his lade, and gropes in the darke if it be poſſible to find him, and lights vpon the dead one, kicks to rouſe him vp, but all in vaine, he will not ſtirre. The poore man in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity is almoſt at his wits end: but ſpying a Candle ſome Bowes ſhoot before him, he makes towards it, and within a little ſpace finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe within <hi>Debtford,</hi> there he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires for a Farrier or a Smith, they direct him to his houſe. But Vulcan had got a cup in his pate, and was gone to bed, he is earneſt to haue him riſe: but the Smith will not by any meanes, vnleſſe hee will giue him a crowne in hand, which is done. Vp gets the Smith, cals his man to carry a Candle, and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne, he tels him all his misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune by the way, and directs him to the place of his diſtaſter, intreating him to vſe all the art he can in the recouery of his horſe, being but
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:21212:102"/> hyred. By this time they come to the ſad ſpectacle, the ſmith lifts at his head, &amp; his man at the taile; but finding no motion, giue him ouer as loſt. The Vintner looking ſadly vpon the buſineſſe, fetcheth a great ſigh, and ſaith, whilſt I haue beene knocking vp the ſmith, ſome body hath ſtolne away my bridle and ſaddle. Back to the Towne goeth he with the Farrier and his man, reſoluing to ſit vp that night, and to comfort himſelfe with a cup of good Ale, to which the Smith brings him, where I leaue them potting together, and from thence looke backe to <hi>Greenwich.</hi> The morning comes, where my late drouſie Vintners are freſh, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and gallopping through <hi>Debtford,</hi> are ſpyde by their fift companion, who cals after them, they wonder to ſee him there, and askt if he had done their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations to their Wiues, hee intreats them to leaue off their
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:21212:102"/> ieſting, and tels them all the former circumſtances of his laſt nights misfortune: ſome laught at him, others lament with him, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their ſeuerall humours, and with this diſcourſe he on foote, and they on horſebacke haue left the Towne a mile behinde them, when one of them caſting his eye of the one ſide, ſpyes a horſe brideled and ſadled, browſing on the hedge, and ſaith withall, is not that the beaſt you rid on? He dares not acknowledge him. That is ſure the ſame Saddle &amp; Bridle ſaith another, or very like them, but hee hath ſcarce faith to beleeue it. At length all of them agree, that both horſe &amp; furniture are the ſame, but he can hardly be wonne, being ſure to pay for one, to hazzard the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſtealing another. But at length they preuaile with him, vp hee mounts, the Stirrops fit him and deliuering him at the ſtable from whence he hyred him, is by
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:21212:103"/> the owner acknowledged for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>183. Two ſtriuing for the Wall.</head>
               <p>TWo Gentlemen meeting, the one iuſtled the other from the wall, and had almoſt made him to meaſure his length in the Kennell, who by much a doe hauing reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered himſelfe, came vp cloſe to him, and askt him whether he were in ieſt, or in earneſt? He told him plainly, that what hee did, was in earneſt. And I am very glad you haue told me ſo, for I proteſt I loue no ſuch ieſting ſaith the other. By which words hee put off the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:21212:103"/>
               <head>184. The anſwer of a Doctor.</head>
               <p>A Worthy Doctor of <hi>Cambridge</hi> amongſt many other charitable deedes done in his life time, at his owne charge made a faire cauſey or high way ſome mile in length, to the great benefit of the Countrey; and being one day there in perſon to viſit the labourers, and to ſee how the worke went forward, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that a Nobleman riding that way by chance, and knowing him, gaue him a kinde ſalutation; but withall thinking to breake a ieſt on him, Maſter Doctor ſaith hee, for all your great charge and paines, yet I beleeue not ſaith hee that this is the high way to Heauen. I am of your minde in that my Lord, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Doctor, for if it were, I ſhould haue wondred to haue met your Lordſhip here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:21212:104"/>
               <head>185. A Horſecourſer.</head>
               <p>ONe comming into <hi>Smithfield</hi> on a Friday market, call'd to a Horſecourſer aloud, and ſaid, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee my friend, how goe horſes to day? To whom hee anſwered, marry as you ſee, ſome amble, ſome trot, and ſome gallop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>186. A Countrey fellow hunting with the King.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Iames</hi> being a hunting and very earneſt in his ſport, a Countrey fellow croſt it, in ſo much that the dogs were at a loſſe: At which the King being extreamely angry, drew his Skeine, and rides after the man, with all the ſpeed he poſſibly can. Who perceiuing the King to purſue him in his anger, cryed out aloud, I beſeech your Maieſty to pardon me, for I haue no deſire to be knighted yet: and this
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:21212:104"/> hee ſpoke ſo often, that hee turned the Kings rage into laughter, who bid him to ride faſt enough, and farre enough and bee hang'd, for he better deſerued a halter, then to be knighted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>187. Women Writers.</head>
               <p>ONe asking a queſtion why wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men either all, or the moſt part, when they learne to write, practiſe Romane hand, It was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him againe, that it ſtood with great reaſon, for he had neuer heard of any woman, that made good Secretary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:21212:105"/>
               <head>188. A Country fellow at a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Table.</head>
               <p>A Country fellow being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Gentlemans table, fell vpon the Artichokes at lower end, and eating the burres was almoſt choakt, ſaith one that ſate nere him, friend why are you buſie with them ſo ſoone, being a diſh reſerued for the laſt, to whom hee anſwered as well as he could ſpeake, Marry I am of your minde, for I thinke they are the laſt diſh that ever I ſhall taſte of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>189. Of curtaling names.</head>
               <p>A Gallant about this Towne, that was admitted into the company of the prime, and choiceſt Gentlemen, vſed to curtall their names, and onely to call them <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, Will, Iack, Dick,</hi> and <hi>Tom,</hi> and being asked why he was ſo familiar with men of that ranke and quality,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:21212:105"/> to giue them no better attributes and titles, anſwered it is my humor, and I vow withall, that if the King ſhould call mee <hi>Iacke,</hi> I would call him <hi>Charles</hi> by the grace of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>190. A retort betwixt two Gentlemen.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman whoſe name was <hi>Apollo,</hi> being very low of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but richly conceited, comming into anothers Chamber whoſe name was Maſter <hi>Towers,</hi> and finding him abſent, who becauſe hee was a big man, and looking vpright vſed an affected gate, finding paper, pen, and inke there, writ this hexameter,</p>
               <q>Interris habitas ſed non in turribus altis.</q>
               <p>The other comming in, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hand, ſent him the ſame line with another vnderwritten.</p>
               <q>Die quibus in terris, &amp; eris mihi magnus Apollo.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:21212:106"/>
               <head>190. A Knight and his man.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman hauing a Seruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who vſed ſtill to ride with his head in his boſome, for which he had often checkt him, but neuer made him reforme it, vpon a time riding to a Noblemans houſe not far of about ſome vrgent buſines, whilſt the Maſter was buſie with the Lord in his Chamber, the Gentlemen had got the man into the Cellar where they had giuen him as much drinke as his skin would hold: in the <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim</hi> his Maſter hauing diſpath this buſineſſe, came ſuddenly and called his man to get his horſe ready, which he did, in the way home the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter obſeruing that contrary to his former cuſtome he rid vpright with his chin almoſt leuell to his noſe, askt him the reaſon why now more then at other times hee rid bolt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; Marry Sir ſaith he, if you will needs know, it is to keepe in my drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:21212:106"/>
               <head>191. A Doctor of Phyſicke, and a Serving man.</head>
               <p>ONe thinking to put a trick vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an excellent D. of Phyſicke, had mingled with the water in his Vrinall the powder of a brick batt, which ſettled to the bottom ſhewes like red grauell, that comes from the kidneyes, he ſhewes it to the Doctor, and tells him that it was his Maſters water, who lay in grieuous paine, deſiring his Worſhips counſel, what would giue him ſome eaſe, the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. chafed it vp and downe, and tried it by the fire; In concluſion found out the fellowes knauery, and cunningly cloſing with him, my friend ſaith he, wouldſt thou haue my counſell to preuent this terrible diſeaſe which is growing on thy M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>? yes ſir ſaith he, that was the cauſe of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to your Worſhip. Then tell him, replyed the Doctor, all that I
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:21212:107"/> can preſcribe him at this time, is that he eate no more Artichokes, and at that word, broke the Vrinall vpon his pate, and ſo left him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>192. One that parted a Fray.</head>
               <p>ONe parting a Fray was cut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the skull, and comming to be dreſt, as hee was ſearching the wound, ſaith he, here is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Orifice, your pery-cranium is pierced, ſo that one may plainly ſee your braines beat, I doe not beleeue that ſaith the patient, for had I had any braines at all, I ſhould neuer haue beene ſo mad, as to haue come betwixt them to part the Fray.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>193. A bargaine in Smithfield.</head>
               <p>A Pleaſant fellow willing to put off a Lame Horſe, rid him from the Sunne Taverne within <hi>Cripple-gate,</hi> to the Sunne in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne,</hi> neere to <hi>Fullers</hi> Rents, and
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:21212:107"/> the next day offering him to ſell him in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> the buyer asking him, why he looked ſo leane. Marry no marvell anſwered hee, for but yeſterday, I rid him from Sunne to Sunne, and neuer drew bridle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <head>194. An Vſurer dying.</head>
               <p>AN Vſurer being dead, was opened, and found without a Heart, at which the ſtanders by as well as the Surgeon wondered, but none could giue a reaſon of the Prodegie, at length ſaith one of the Executors, it may bee his heart now hee is dead, is where it was when he was liuing, and looking in his Cheſt where his money lay: they found it there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="joke">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:21212:108"/>
               <head>195. A Doctor and a Scholler.</head>
               <p>A Doctor of the Vniverſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of more ſtanding then lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being at Dinner in the Hall, and hearing a fellow Commoner ſpeake lowder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt, calls to a Iunior Scholler that waited, and ſaid goe to that Gentleman from me, and tell him <hi>Vir ſapit, qui pauca loquitur,</hi> which being delivered him, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me ſaith hee, to M. Doctor, and tell him that I ſay <hi>Vir loquitur, qui pauca ſapit,</hi> which inverſion leſt it be iuſtly aſperſt on me, here I ſet my period.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21212:108"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
